<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against bigotry in religion, or, A discourse proving from the testimony of kings, nobles, judges, bishops, deans, doctors, &amp;c. that wise and good men may differ one from another both in doctrine and discipline, and maintain Christian charity amongst themselves / by a True Berean.</title>
            <author>True Berean.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3491A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43601</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475008</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475008</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2243:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against bigotry in religion, or, A discourse proving from the testimony of kings, nobles, judges, bishops, deans, doctors, &amp;c. that wise and good men may differ one from another both in doctrine and discipline, and maintain Christian charity amongst themselves / by a True Berean.</title>
                  <author>True Berean.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16, 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: Some faded print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Congregational Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST BIGOTRY IN RELIGION: OR, A DISCOURSE proving from the Teſtimony of Kings, Nobles, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Biſhops, Deans, Doctors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Wiſe and Good Men may differ one from another both in Doctrine and Diſcipline, and maintain Chriſtian Charity amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a true</hi> Berean.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:151109:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151109:2"/>
            <head>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST BIGOTRY IN RELIGION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is a Matter of great Lamentation to conſider of the Decay of true Primitive Chriſtianity, and that inſtead of it is ſprung up Bigotiſm on the one ſide, and Scepticiſm on the other: Never was there more need to call for Engines and Buckets to quench the Flames of Contention now kindled amongſt us, upon the account of different Modes of Worſhip, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Points of Doctrine.</p>
            <p>My Deſign is not to Applaud or Condemn any one party of Chriſtians among us, but to perſwade them all to be Humble and Charitable, and to believe that they have finite Underſtandings and fallible Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ought not to be peremptory for or againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151109:3"/> little things; nor too poſitive in any thing, but thoſe great things wherein Chriſtians are all agreed.</p>
            <p>I would gladly know why another Man may not differ from me with the ſame Sincerity that I differ from him, and why he may not as well call me a Knave or Fool for not being of his mind, as I call him ſo for his not being of mine.</p>
            <p>I may well ask the old Queſtion, Which way went the Spirit of God from him to me, that I ſhould ſmite my Fellow-ſervant with my Hand, Tongue or Pen? I hope the Sentiments of theſe great Men in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing pages will make the World more Modeſt for the future: I am ſure we have ſeen little good produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by all our Clamorous Reflections one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; God help us: Every Party amongſt us Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends ſo eagerly for our ſeveral Forms, that we have almoſt loſt the Power, and our Bigotry for Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials hath almoſt ſwallowed up our true Zeal for the ſubſtantial part of Religion.</p>
            <p>There is Truth enough among all Parties to Save Men, and Malice enough to Dam Angels. I think true Religion conſiſts in our Love to God and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: I am ſure our Great Lord and Maſter has told us ſo, and I will venture my Salvation upon his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; for whoever wants thoſe Qualifications, is as far from Eternal Bleſſedneſs as a <hi>Jew</hi> or a <hi>Mahometan,</hi> notwithſtanding his Bigotry for his particular Mode of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>We have abundance of Proteſtant Popery now in <hi>England,</hi> and think our ſelves as infallible in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches as they do in theirs, and make no ſcruple to caſt all ſuch into our fiery Furna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who will not Bow down to the Images of our Imaginations, did not our Laws tye our Hands behind us.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen ſeveral Forms uppermoſt in <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151109:3"/> at one time or other, but wiſe men are Indifferent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout indifferent things, and ſubmit them to the Wiſdom of their Superiors. So long as God's Word is truly preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, Peace and good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der preſerved, they trouble not themſelves, about Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, Geſture, Time and Place.</p>
            <p>If there were a General Council called to reſolve this Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> which among all the ſeveral Parties now in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> are moſt in the right? I am perſwaded they would be voted the wiſeſt men and the beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians who are of no Sect or Party, but chooſe out of all that which is moſt agreeable to Truth and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and tends moſt to promote the Glory of God and the Salvation of Men.</p>
            <p>They are certainly in the ſureſt way to Heaven who moſt abound with ſincere Piety and Catholick Charity, and can hold Communion with any true Church of Chriſt which is ſound in the Subſtantials of Religion; notwithſtanding ſome different Modes of Adminiſtration, ſo long as nothing is required which they judge to be ſinful.</p>
            <p>Give me the true Evangelical Catholick, that does not confine Salvation to his own particular Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor call every man a Heretick that is not of his private Perſwaſion. God Almighty never required of men an exact uniformity in Eccleſiaſtical Ceremonies nor Syſtimatical Opinions, but he has made our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Damnation depend upon our Faith and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and they are very conſiſtent with divers ways of Worſhip, and with variety of Apprehenſions in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine matters.</p>
            <p>The moſt wiſe and ſagacious men among all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have exclaimed againſt Bigotry in Religion, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when their thoughts have run pure from dregs of ſecular Intereſt: But if once they have been biaſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the fears of Diſpleaſing a popular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151109:4"/> or by the hopes of obtaining ſome Eccleſiaſtical Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they have then diſcover'd a mighty Zeal for the ſilver Shrines of <hi>Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can truly ſay with the Reverend Dr. <hi>Tenniſon,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> that I heartily thank God I have found in Converſation ſo much of good Temper and real Piety in many Men, upon whom Raſhneſs had fixed Names of Infamy. [Epiſt. to his <hi>Spittle</hi> Sermon, 1681.]</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> gives this Character of the Inhabitants of the Pariſh of <hi>Kidderminſter</hi> in <hi>Worſter-ſhire,</hi> whereof he was Miniſter, <hi>viz.</hi> the things which I loved in you I will freely praiſe, which were a ſpecial meaſure of Humility, a plain Simplicity in Religion, a Freedom from the Common Errors of the Times, a readineſs to receive the Truth, a Catholick Temper, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictedneſs to any Sect; an exemption from Schiſm and Separating ways, a hatred and diſowning of the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations and Rebellions againſt the Civil Government, an open bearing of Teſtimony in all theſe Caſes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Seriouſneſs in Religion, and a ſober, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, charitable and godly Converſation.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> has told the World, that they, meaning the Independants, never entertained a Thought uncharitable to ſuch a Prodigy of Inſolence, as to exclude any ſort of Chriſtians from an Intereſt in the Love of God, or Grace of Chriſt, or Hopes of Salvation, becauſe they do not, or will not comply with thoſe ways and Terms of Church-Communion which they approve of. How far, ſaith the ſame Dr. Errors in Judgment, or miſcariages in ſacred Worſhip, which any ſort of Profeſſors have ſuperadded unto Divine Truth, may be of ſo pernicious a Nature, as to hinder them from an Intereſt in the Covenant, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice their Eternal Salvation, God only knows.</p>
            <p>But the Notion, ſays he, we have concerning the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Will of God in Scripture, do perſwade us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151109:4"/> that where men do in ſincerity improve the Abli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and means of Kowledge of Divine Truth wherewith they are intruſted, endeavouring withall to Anſwer their Light and Convictions with a ſuitable Obedience, there are but few Errours of Mind, of ſo malignant a Nature, as abſolutely to exclude ſuch Perſons from an Intereſt in Eternal Mercy. And we look upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or the Generality of the Nation Profeſſing the Chriſtian Religion (meaſuring them by the Doctrine that has been preached to them, and received by them, ſince the Reformation) to be as Sound and Healthful a part of the Catholick Church as any in the World, and we wholly deny that the Miſtakes and Diſorders of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in complying with, or joyning themſelves unto, ſuch Churches as we think have no warrantable Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, ought to be any Cauſe of the diminiſhing of our Love towards them.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Tombs,</hi> the moſt Learned Anabaptiſt that ever I converſt with, does very much Lament the great Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities amongſt Chriſtians, and the ſad Face of things in <hi>Europe</hi> upon that account; which, ſaith he, ſhould move every Tender-hearted Chriſtian to endeavour to allay thoſe heats, leſt a deluge of Popery or Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metaniſm overwhelm us; for though Difference in Opinion ſhould be incurable, yet Diſcords among Chriſtians are not incurable, ſo long as they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the Subſtantials of Religion. And he gives ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unanſwerable Reaſons to prove that we ought not to be ſo abridged of our Chriſtian Liberty to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to hear only one ſort of Preachers, when it may be more for our Edification ſometimes to hear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and he blames thoſe who will not ſometimes hear a Godly, Learned, Conformable Divine, in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood; and he ſays, that more good has been done by the Preaching of Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, Potter, Abbot, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, Sibbs, Dod, Ball, Perkins, Hilderſham, Wheatly, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151109:5"/> and ſuch Pious Epiſcopal Men, than by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of rigid Separatiſts.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Bampfield,</hi> altho' he were for the Obſervation of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, yet expreſſes himſelf with great Charity and Reſpect towards thoſe who differed from him, confeſſes the Darkneſs of his own Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in Divine Truths, and Subſcribes to thoſe who have a clearer Knowledge in the Mind of Chriſt, tho' he concludes himſelf to be in the right, yet he ſees no Reaſon for quarreling with thoſe whom he fears to be in the wrong.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſſander</hi> a learned Romaniſt, ſpeaking of thoſe who were fallen from their Church, and numbered among Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, it is, ſaith he, to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how rightly and juſtly this is determined of them? For there is to be conſidered as to the Church, the Head and the Body; from the Head there is no departure but by Doctrine, diſagreeable to Chriſt the Head; from the Body there is no departure by diverſity of Rights and Opinions, but only by the defect of Charity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Keith,</hi> a Learned Quaker, writing againſt Dr. <hi>Bajer,</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Germany,</hi> is ſo Candid as to tell his Adverſary that he writes ſoberly and fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thoſe things which he imputes to them, meaning the Quakers, as falſe and erroneous, and he ſuppoſes his Adverſaries Miſtakes not to flow from Hatred or Malice of Mind, which is too frequent in many others, but of ſome defect of right Reaſon and Judgment, and an Error of Humane Weakneſs. Such is his great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which I wiſh were imitated by thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be more Orthodox.</p>
            <p>I do not believe that every Chriſtian is bound to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the exact meaning of every difficult Text in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, but I think we are all obliged to practice every Precept of our Saviour's Sermon on the Mount. My Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales</hi> has well obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151109:5"/> that there are many obſtruſe Points, furiouſly agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt Divines that are not neceſſary to be known, nor poſſible to be underſtood, without a clearer Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God; as particularly the Nature of the Divine Decrees, and what influence they have upon the Minds of Men; the reſiſtibility and irreſiſtibility of Divine Grace; the manner of the Exiſtence of Three Perſons in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Eſſence; the way of the tranſmiſſion of Original Sin from the Parents to the Child; the Extent of Chriiſt's Sacrifice, and how far it was intentially for all or ſome; the Nature of the Will of Man, and how it operates towards his Converſion; wherein the formal Nature of Juſtification conſiſts, and how far Faith ſingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered is ſufficient without habitual Holineſs. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation of Preſcience and Predetermination with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Actions, and contingent Events, with many more ſuch Nice Points, which wiſe and good Men humbly enquire into, but brand not their Brethren with Malice or Hypocriſie, becauſe they differ from them in theſe things.</p>
            <p>The great <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Boyl</hi> tells us concerning the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and the <hi>Arminians,</hi> that the truly Pious of either Party are perhaps otherwiſe lookt upon by God than by one another, as contending which of the Divine Attributes ſhould be moſt reſpected and honoured, the one ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to affirm irreſpective Decrees, to magnifie his Goodneſs, and the other to deny them to ſecure the Credit of his Juſtice; the one Party thinks Grace more magnify'd by believing it ſo irreſiſtible, that to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever its intended he cannot but be happy; and the other thinks Free-Grace moſt extoll'd by believing it ſo univerſal that it will make every man happy if he himſelf pleaſes; the one conſigns to it an unlimited vaſt extent, and the other an infallible victorious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151109:6"/>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Burton</hi> in his Sermons tells us, that the way to Unity among Chriſtians, is to ſuppoſe our ſelves fallible in our Interpretations; and to give our Brethren Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of judging what is the true Sence and Meaning of the Scriptures, as well as our ſelves; if we can but think the Words capable of the Senſe they give, or can believe they think it ſo, though we do not; ſo long as it does not overthrow the Foundations of Faith and Holineſs, or ſuppoſe to us it ſeems to do ſo, ſo long as it does not ſo in them, let us bear with one another.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Charnock</hi> obſerves, though there be a ſmoak in the Temple, yet ſo long as God has a Temple ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Ordinances kept up, let us imitate the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the old Puritans, and love all Chriſt's Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Callamy</hi> in his Sermon before the Parliament men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions one that Diſputed ſo long about the five Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Points in the Schools 'till he had forgot the ſix Petitions in the Lord's Prayer. If Men do but own the Merit of Chriſt in our Juſtification, and the Spirit of Chriſt in our Sanctification, let us own them as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> preaching before K. <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelf thus: <q>Good Lord, what uncharitable Cenſures are Men apt to paſs upon each other; let a Man be ſtrict in Moral and Divine Duties, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo peaceable, he is a Puritan, and every Puritan is a Hypocrite; let him be more Free in Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though never ſo Conſcientious, then he is a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine; let him ſcruple ſome innovated Form and he is a Schiſmatick; let him ſtand for Ancient Order and Government, and then he is a Formaliſt: in the mean Time, who can eſcape free, ſurely I that blame both ſhall be ſure to be cenſured by both, ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151109:6"/> be, Yes, I am to purpoſe, therein I rejoice, and will rejoice: What! a Neuter ſays one? what, on both ſides ſays another? this is what I looked for, Yes, true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Brethren, you have hit it right; I am, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my ſelf to be as the Terms ſtand, on neither, and yet of both parts. I am for the Peace of both, for the Humour of neither, I wiſh all my Brethren were of my Mind, our Land would not then be thus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted: This Man is right and ſound, that Man is wrong and rotten; how ſo dear Chriſtians! What for Ceremonies and Circumſtances? Let me tell you, that Man is right, whoſe Heart is right with God, whatever Form he is for.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> obſerves, that ſome amongſt us, who think themſelves withoult fault, have thrown ſo many Stones at their Brethren who differ from them, that they have daſht out the Brains of Peace, and buried it in their Contentions; and we have cauſe to fear an Earthquake to roll away the Stone from the Mouth of the Sepulchre, before we can expect a Reſurrection of Charity.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> obſerves, that as the Chriſtian Church has grown more Carnal, ſo it has grown more Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and as more Contentious, ſo more and more Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the preſent moſt deplorable ſtate of Things; Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Intereſt is every where deſigned by one Party and another, and by wiſhing the Proſperity of the Church, is only meant the Proſperity of our own Party: So that there can be no truly united Prayers or Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for any common Good, but what ſeems deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by ſome, is dreaded by others, and for 1400 Years the Church has been ſhattered and parcell'd out into no Body knows how many ſorts of Communions: And inſtead of ſound Knowledge, of the Few, Clear, and great Things of Religion, we have ſpent our time in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151109:7"/> Doubtful Opinions, Diſputable Points, Logical Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Metaphyſical Niceties, Affected Formalities and Feigned Shews of Devotion, which muſt ſerve inſtead of Regular Converſations, and make amends and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone for the vileſt Practices; and People muſt be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted from attending the Miniſtry of ſuch who uſe apt and proper Methods to ſave Souls, by being told they are <hi>Antinomians</hi> or <hi>Arminians,</hi> &amp;c. when upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry it may be found they deteſt the Doctrines im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to them.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Manton</hi> in his Sermon before the Parliament, gives Advice in Order to the promoting of Unity, that Men ſhould not impropriate Chriſt to any one Party or ſort of Profeſſors, forasmuch as the Apoſtle reproves thoſe that ſaid <hi>I am of Chriſt</hi> as well as thoſe that ſaid <hi>I am of Paul;</hi> that is, thoſe that ſpeak as if Chriſt were only theirs: They were a Faction. St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Dialect was to all that call on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, both their Lord and ours. It proves fatal to Religion when Men cry up Names, and theſe Names beget Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Factions, to the hazard of the publick Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Edwin Sands,</hi> that curious Traveller, obſerves, that in all Religions where he has been the moſt Virtuous People are moſt reſpected and reverenced, except amongſt Chriſtians; and he gives this Reaſon, becauſe we have ſuperadded to our ſeeming Piety ſuperſtitious, pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical or troubleſome qualities, which forfeits the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Wiſdom, and makes us deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Temple</hi> takes Notice that in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> they have one Diſeaſe which threatens the Death and Ruine of their State, and that is Bigotry for their particular Parties, and their extravagant Conteſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Factions of <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts:</hi> And he wiſely obſerves that the way to our future
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151109:7"/> Happineſs has been perpetually diſputed throughout the World, and muſt be left at laſt to the impreſſions made upon every Man's Belief and Conſcience, either by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or ſupernatural means, which Impreſſions Men may diſguiſe or diſſemble, but no man can reſiſt; for belief is no more in a Mans Power then his Stature or his Feature, and he that tells me, I muſt change my Opinion for his, becauſe his is truer or better, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving me a Reaſon for it to convince my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, may as well tell me, I muſt change my Gray Eyes, for his that are Black, becauſe they are Loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Purer in eſteem. If he ſays, I muſt inform my ſelf, he ſpeaks Reaſon, if I do it not; but if I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it all I can, and perhaps more then ever he did, and yet ſtill differ from him; I eaſily underſtand what he means by informing my ſelf, which is in ſhort, that I muſt do it, untill I come to be of his Opinion. If he tells me, that Ignorance, or Paſſion, or Prejudice blinds me, that I cannot ſee the Truth, he ſays nothing, unleſs he proves it; for at the ſame time I paſt for one as well in my Sences as he, as Pertinent in Talk and as Prudent in Life. How he ſhould come to know me better then I know my ſelf, I cannot tell, nor why his underſtanding muſt be the general ſtandard of Truth.</p>
            <p>The preſent Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> whoſe Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is known to all Men, has told the World that the Biggots and Zealots of all parties have got a Scurvey trick of lying for the Truth; ſee his Sermon before the King.</p>
            <p>The preſent Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> ſaith in his Sermon before the Parliament, <q>That we often make Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſt in Opinion and outward Profeſſion; if we have but once joined our ſelves with that Party of Chriſtians which we think in the right, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151109:8"/> eſpouſed all their Controverſies, and are zealous for the obſervance of their particular Forms; we think we are true Chriſtians, let our Morals be what they will: As for inſtance, if I am true to the Principles of a ſeparate Congregation, and vigorous in oppoſing all thoſe that are not of my way, though I be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable and cenſorious, and affront Authority and contemn good Laws, yet I think the Relation I ſtand in to the People of God will bear me out; on the other ſide, if I be a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I am apt to think my ſelf in the way to Heaven, if I be but ſtout for the Church, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous againſt Sectaries, and punctual in obſerving Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, though I have nothing of the Life and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſtianity in me, nor of that Sobriety, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Charity which our Saviour requires of all his Followers.</q> Thus that great Man ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> has ſufficiently expoſed and reproved the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotry of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> who had a zeal for God, but not according to Knowledge, and ſo relied upon their Judaical Forms, inſtead of the Power of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>The Learned Lord <hi>Faulkland</hi> has unanſwerably Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed all pretences to Infallibility, not only in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, but in any other particular Communion, and thus demonſtrated the Vanity and Miſchief of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in Matters of Religion, and pleaded for mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual forbearance and Chriſtian Moderation one towards another.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> well obſerves, if Swords and Racks, Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets and Fires, are proper Methods for Converting Men to Religion, the greateſt Tyrants are the moſt infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Teachers. Our Saviours Kingdom was introduced into the World by doing good and ſuffering evil, he opened the way for his Goſpel, not by killing his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, but by dying himſelf and requiring his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151109:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> to dye for the Truth, and he propogated his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by ſuitable means; namely by the Illumination of Mens Minds, Perſwaſion of their Wills, drawing their Affections to embrace it: Thus the Dr. has declared his Antipathy to an irregular zeal, which commonly ends in Perſecution either of the Hand or of the Tongue.</p>
            <p>A Learned Man now amongſt us, who hath given the World a clear Demonſtration of the Excellency of Humane Underſtanding, tells us, that the only way to put an end to all Religious Diſputes is to hold faſt the Form of ſound Words deliver'd to us by inſpired Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and expreſs our Creeds in the Language of the Holy Ghoſt; foraſmuch as all Chriſtians properly ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, differ but in one thing, and that is the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Penman. All Parties agree in the Text, but differ in the Comment. And its our duty like the Noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> not only to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures but to try the Spirits of the Expoſitors, that we may not be impoſed on by Bigots, who call their Gloſſes Rules of Faith; when <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> muſt interpret St. <hi>Paul,</hi> we have Humane Conſequences and Concluſions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Divine Revelations; and by the Help of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, the Poor Fiſhermen muſt ſpeak Metaphyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; perhaps if we had never found any other Creeds than what were made by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, it had been better with <hi>Chriſtendom:</hi> Its great Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for any to undertake the wording of Creeds for others, and then to repreſent that Faith as inſufficient, which is not deliver'd in their Terms and Phraſe, and to deny thoſe Perſons to be Members of Chriſt, who conſcientiouſly refuſe to ſubſcribe to any other Draught then their great Lord hath given them. Our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father hath left us his Laſt Will and Teſtament ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Plain and Intelligible, in all thats neceſſary to be known, but ſome of his Fooliſh Children pretending to explain it, have perplext it; and thereby ſome of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151109:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Legatees are like to be cheated, and ſome muſt be ſent to a General Council, ſome to a Convocation, and ſome to an Aſſembly to know the meaning of it; when Himſelf hath told us, <hi>If we ſincerely ſeek and worſhip him, we ſhall know the Doctrines, whether they be of God.</hi> When we conſider the ſmallneſs of the Writings of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, the ſhortneſs of Chriſts Sermons, the fewneſs of the Epiſtles writ by the Apoſtles; and the many large Volumes of Commentators and Criticks ſince, we may ſay the Text is ſwallowed up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Truth lies hid rather then revealed. Men darken the Divine Councils by Words without Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, it's not enough for ſome men to know there is a God, and that he is one, and Holy, Juſt and Good, the Obſerver of their Actions, and Rewarder of their Deeds; but they muſt be diſtinctly informed of his Nature, his Purpoſes and Decrees, and of the ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them all to the Line of their Underſtandings, and yet they know not themſelves; it will not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them that Chriſt is the Son of God, and that he died for the Sins of Men, but they muſt know the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of the Relation, and after what Manner he is the Son of God; Whether he be the Cauſe, or Effect of Gods Love? What was the Price he paid? Whether he were offered to all or ſome? and what the Spirit is? Whether it proceed from the Father, or the Son? Whether it be a Perſon, how it exiſts? and Rail at their Brethren, if they don't uſe the ſame Words.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151109:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Conformiſts Acknowledge that there are Good and Worthy Men among the Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIſhop Jewel in Anſwer to Mr. Harding;</hi> The thing is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and may be yielded to, ſaith the one Sect; The other that they be the Popes rags, and may not be worn: <hi>Saith Jewel,</hi> the Godly Learned men, at whoſe perſons you ſo rudely ſcoffe, that refuſe to go in your Apparel, or otherwiſe to ſhew themſelves like you, have age ſufficient, and can anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Notwithſtanding, thus much I may ſay in their behalf, neither do they commend any manner of Apparel, as holy, nor condemn any manner of Apparel, as unholy. That is your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar Error, Mr. <hi>Harding</hi> to make ſo deep account of outward ſhews. They may juſtly ſay the ſame Apparel on your parts hath been fouly abuſed, &amp;c. <hi>Defence of the Apology, part.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 325.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Or King</hi> James the firſt <hi>Inſtructions to his Son;</hi> I do equally Love and Honour the Learned and Grave Men of either of theſe opinions, (<hi>i. e.</hi> for or againſt Ceremonials) which for mine own part I ever held indifferent. Again I exhort my Son to be beneficial to the good men of the Miniſtry, praiſing God, that there is a ſufficient number of good men of them in this Kingdom, <hi>(i. e.</hi> of <hi>Scotland;)</hi> and yet are they all known to be againſt the form of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Speech of the Biſhop of St.</hi> Davids, (<hi>Dr.</hi> Rudde) <hi>in the Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, May</hi> 23. 1604; I put a great difference between them that are Schiſmatical, or open diſturbers of the ſtate Eccleſiaſtical eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and them that are ſcrupulous only of ſome Ceremonies, and other circumſtances, being otherwiſe Learned, Studious, Grave and Honeſt Men, and whoſe labours have been both painful in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151109:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151109:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151109:11"/> Church, and profitable to their ſeveral Congregations: Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Preachers laſt mentioned, I ſuppoſe, that if upon urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to the uſe of Ceremonies and Attire preſcribed, they ſhould ſtand out ſtifly, and chooſe rather to forgo their Livings and exerciſe of their Miniſtry; and tho I do not juſtifie their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings therein, yet ſurely there ſervice would be miſſed at ſuch a time, as need ſhall require them and us to give the right hand of Fellowſhip one to another, and to go Arm in Arm againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Adverſary, that ſo there might be, <hi>Vis unita fortior,</hi> &amp;c. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo remember that when the <hi>Benjamites</hi> (though for their deſert in maintaining of a bad cauſe) were all deſtroyed ſaving ſix hundred, and the Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſware in their fury that none of them would give his daughter to the <hi>Benjamites</hi> to Wife: yet when their hot blood was over they lamented, and ſaid there is one Tribe cut off from <hi>Iſrael</hi> this day, and they uſed all their wits to the utmoſt of their Policy to reſtore that Tribe again: In like ſort, if theſe our Brethren aforeſaid ſhould be deprived of their places for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters premiſed, I think we ſhould find cauſe to bend our wits to the uttermoſt extent of our skill to provide ſome Cure of Souls for them, where they may exerciſe their Talents; verily I know not where to find ſo many able Preachers within this Realm (unprovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for) to ſucceed them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hookers Eccleſ. Pol. Pref.</hi> Otherwiſe (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſet aſide their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Miſconceits, ſpeaking of the Diſſenters) right well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and moſt Religiouſly enclined minds. Again, heartily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching you by the meekneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, whom I truſt, ye love, that as ye tender the peace and quietneſs of the Church; If your own Souls, hearts and conſciences be, as I doubt not but they are, things moſt dear and pretious unto you, be not blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with partialities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Halls <hi>Apology againſt the Browniſt, p.</hi> 137, <hi>and</hi> 138. <hi>Sect.</hi> 56. <hi>Edit.</hi> 1610: Thoſe men which you ſay complain ſo much of their miſerable condition under the Prelats impoſitions, have not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding with the ſame Pens and Tongues not only juſtified our Church, but extolled it. You have found no ſharper Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries in this very accuſation, for which you maliciouſly cite them. How freely; how fully, have they evinced the Truth! Yea the happineſs of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt your falſe Challenges: and your forehead dares challenge them for Authors! So hath their Moderation oppoſed ſome appendancies, that they have both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151109:11"/> and defended the ſubſtance with equal vehemence to your oppoſition; neither do they ſuffer (as you traduce them) for ſeeking another Church Government.—Would God you could follow thoſe men in Moderate and Charitable carriage, as you have outrun them in complaints!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Crakanthorp <hi>In his Defenſio Eccleſiae Anglicanae ch.</hi> 33. <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. <hi>Puritanum, qui Haereticus ſit, tu, opinor, in</hi> Anglia <hi>nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem unquam comſpexiſti.</hi>— You never ſaw in <hi>England,</hi> I believe, any Puritan Heretical in his Judgment.— <hi>Certe eorum ferè nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, cui quiſquam inter vos pietate, &amp; vitae Sanctimoniâ, doctrinâ etiam (ne tu quidem, qui Magiſter es in tuo Iſraele) paucis eorum conferendus es.</hi> Certainly, ſcarce any one of them, with whom any men of yours can be compared in Holineſs of Life, in Learning alſo (not you indeed who are a Maſter in your <hi>Iſrael</hi>) worthy to be named in compariſon with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Edward Bulkley <hi>in his Apology for the Religion Eſtabliſhed, being an Anſwer to</hi> Wrights <hi>Articles, Edit.</hi> 1608. <hi>Art.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 105, 106. There is neither Proteſtant, nor ſuch as it pleaſeth you to call <hi>Puritans,</hi> ſo far forth as I know and believe, but as they deny the Popes wicked Supremacy, which he hath uſurped over the Church of God, and Soveraign Princes, ſo they do unfeignedly confeſs and acknowledge the Kings Power and Authority in his Kingdoms and Dominions, and in all Cauſes, and over all perſons, both Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal, or Political: They all ſay with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that every Soul ought to be ſubject to the higher Powers, whether they be (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith) Apoſtle or Evangeliſt, or Prophet, whatſoever he be,) for this ſubjection doth not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Godlineſs: They all confeſs, that it belongeth to his Royal dignity, to ſee and procure not only Juſtice to be executed, and peace maintained, but alſo that God be truly and ſincerely ſerved, according to his will revealed in his Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrews <hi>Reſponſ. ad</hi> Bellarmini <hi>Apologiam, Edit.</hi> 1610. <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>Bellarm. In</hi> Britanniâ <hi>magna multitudo Puritanorum, qui Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum non ad Regem, ſed ad Senatum Miniſtrorum pertinere: Reſp. Puti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da hac calumnia eſt, Presbyterio forte lis eſt cum Epiſcopis, cum Rege nulla eſt; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trobique regi deſertur ultro, utrinque quod</hi> Caeſaris <hi>eſt</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari <hi>redditur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Caves <hi>Goſpel Preached,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 98. Many of the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> perſwaſion are not only ſound and Orthodox in the main Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Reformed Religion, but Learned and able Defenders
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151109:12"/> of it, zealous Proteſtors againſt all the Horrid wickedneſs of this Day, (<hi>Jan.</hi> 30.) and active Inſtruments in bringing home our Baniſhed King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Burgeſs <hi>Pref. to Vindicat. of our Ceremonies.</hi> Some peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and very worthy Miniſters were caſt out after the Conference at <hi>Hampton Court:</hi> Whereupon it was intended to bring them in by a kind of neceſſity, or to looſen from them others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſtſcript. To Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry.</hi> The modeſty, and excellent temper of ſeveral ancient Non-Conformiſt of this Nation is a fair Copy for thoſe to Write after, that cannot yet be perſwaded to come compleatly over to the Church; and I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat all ſober Non-Conformiſt to remember after the conference at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> when the Non-conformiſts could not obtain their deſire, they were not Tranſported with heat and paſſion; but ingenuouſly promiſed the Biſhops that they would neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Reverence them as ſpiritual Fathers, and joyn with them againſt the common Enemy.</p>
            <p>Hookers <hi>Diſcourſe of Juſtification, p.</hi> 41; I doubt not, but God was merciful to ſave thouſands of our Fathers living in Popiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, inaſmuch as they ſinned ignorantly. <hi>Item p.</hi> 87. That Churches Deceit hath prevailed over none unto death, but only ſuch as took <hi>a pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> They in all ages, whoſe hearts have delighted in the principal Truth, and whoſe Souls have thirſted after Righteouſneſs, if they received the mark of Errour, the mercy of God, even erring and dangerouſly erring, might ſave them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True ſtate of the Primitive Church Epiſtle to the Reader.</hi> I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, there are thouſands of Papiſts, <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> both Learned and Religious, who would lay down their Lives for the Truth they profeſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles the firſt <hi>upon the Covenant Sect.</hi> 4. Touching the Diſcipline and Government of the Church, &amp;c. Things which are of no clear and moral neceſſity, but very diſputable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted among Learned and Godly men, <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. Yet as things now ſtand, good men ſhall leaſt offend God or me, by keeping their Covenant in honeſt and lawful ways, ſince I have the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to think that the cheif end of the Covenant in ſuch mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, was to preſerve Religion in purity and the Kingdoms in peace.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151109:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem,</hi> to the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> Be confident as I am, that the moſt of all ſides who have done amiſs, have done ſo not out of Malice, but miſ-information or miſ-apprehenſion. I alledge this not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or juſtifie thoſe perſons, much leſs their Solemn League or Covenant, but to ſhow his charitable Sentiment of them, allowing good men to have been in the number, lead away with that Error of the times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Seconds Declaration concerning Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,</hi> 1660. <hi>pag.</hi> 5. When we were in <hi>Holland,</hi> we were attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many grave and Learned Miniſters from home, who were looked upon as the moſt able and principal Aſſertors of the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> Opinions, with whom we had as much Conference, as the multitude of Affairs which were then upon us, would permit, and to our great Satisfaction and Comfort, found them perſons full of affection to us, of Zeal for the peace of the Church and State, and neither Enemies (as they have been given out to be) to Epiſcopacy and Liturgy, but modeſtly to deſire ſuch alterations in either, as without ſhaking the Foundations, might beſt allay the preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, which the indiſpoſition of the Times, and Tenderneſs of ſome Mens Conſciences had contracted. <hi>Pag.</hi> 17. <hi>Item,</hi> Becauſe ſome men, otherwiſe Pious, and Learned, ſay, they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form unto the Subſcription required by the Cannon, nor take the Oath of Canonical Obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Appendix to the third part of the Friendly Debate, pag.</hi> 143. Tells us that Doctor <hi>Jackſon</hi> always reverenced their Excellent Parts, and good Labours, though he diſliked the deformity of their Zeal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon <hi>on Rom.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 29. I make no doubt, neither dare I be ſo uncharitable, as not to think, but that many of them (<hi>i. e.</hi> Non-conformiſts) have honeſt, and upright, and ſincere hearts to God-ward, and are unfeignedly Zealous for Gods Truth, and for Religion. They that are ſuch, no doubt feel the Comfort of it in their own Souls, and we ſee the Fruits of it in their Converſations, and rejoyce at it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge</hi> Hales <hi>Diſcourſe of Religion, pag.</hi> 21. Some perſons truly Conſcientious, obſerving the many corruptions that the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church hath brought into the Worſhip of God, are very ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of any thing that may look, as they think, that way; though they are otherwiſe Men, of ſound and Orthodox Principles, and of a truly Righteous and Sober Life. <hi>Item. p.</hi> 13. Scrupulous of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151109:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151109:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151109:14"/> the Ceremonies, otherwiſe ſound in the principles of Faith, Pious and Strict in their Lives, Juſt and Honeſt to all men, and Sober, Temperate and Blameleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Smithies <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs, pag.</hi> 71. It may be, they are good Men, and were converted by that Miniſter, or ſome other of the ſame perſwaſion, from the ways of Wickedneſs, to the practice of Religion: 'Tis well quoted by a late Learned Writer for the Church, in the diviſion of hearts that is in the World, it's certain ſome good may Diſſent. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor <hi>Duct. Dub. P.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. <hi>Rule</hi> 23. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>Item Collect. of Diſcourſe, Epiſt. Dedic. before Liberty of Propheſie.</hi> Its an hard Caſe, that we ſhould think all Papiſts and Anabaptiſts and Sacramentaries bad men; certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among all theſe Sects there are very many Wiſe Men, and Good Men, as well as Erring.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> D' l'Angles <hi>Letter to the Biſhop of London.</hi> It is certain, that among the multitude that follow them (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Separatiſts) there is a very great Number of good Men, whoſe Faith is pure, and whoſe Piety is ſincere; and ſeems to me, that the good and charitable Biſhops ought to ſay of them, though in ſomething a different ſence, as <hi>Optatus Milevitanus</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in his time; <hi>Si Collegium Epiſcopale nobiſcum habere nolunt, tamen fratres ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Stillingfleet <hi>Mischief of Separation. p.</hi> 9. I cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf, that ſo many ſcrupulous, and conſcientious men, as are at this day among us, would live ſo many years in a known ſin, (<hi>i. e</hi> in a ſtate of Separation from the Communion of a Church which in Conſcience they thought themſelves obliged to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformiſts Plea for the Nonconformiſts, Part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 17. Some have their Indiſcretions, and their Miſtakes, and their Heats, and their Blemiſhes; and what Party have not? But if the Grace of God hath appeared to any men, and if any are taught to deny Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs, and Worldly Luſts, and to live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godlily in this preſent World, as I am ſure there are, there are ſuch among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. What an Example was the moſt faithful and ſucceſsful Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> whoſe practice was copied after his <hi>Gildas Salvianus,</hi> and the Miniſters of that Aſſociation? How diligent was Mr. <hi>Stubbs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> and others?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151109:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem pag.</hi> 27. The chief of the Congregational, are Men of great Worth, Learning, Sobriety, and Holineſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> ſuch as are ſimply ſcrupulous in the point of Baptiſm, are reputed peaceable and holy men by them that write againſt them; as Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Obad. Wills,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Joſeph Whiſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, The <hi>Quaker</hi> muſt have the right of Humanity; they who ſcrupled ſwearing did call God to witneſs, and did proteſt and promiſe Loyalty and Obedience: They offered the ſecurity of their words and bodies to the Law when found Tranſgreſſors againſt the Peace: There are many things commendable in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem p.</hi> 101. As far as my Acquaintance doth extend to the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> I muſt do them this Juſtice, that they are of a Loving, Healing, and Uniting Spirit. I have heard them ſpeak very well of good Conformiſts, and as free to acknowledge the Grace of God in them as in thoſe of their own perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Principles and Practice, &amp;c. p.</hi> 28. The matters in Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie (<hi>i. e.</hi> of Conformity) between men of confeſſedly great worth and goodneſs, I declare for my part, and care not who knows it, that I love with my heart a ſober and peaceable minded Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt, as much Conformiſt as I am my ſelf, and I think him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the worſe man, that is ſo; ſuppoſing I perceive him Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious in other Matters, and particularly that he is not of a Cenſorious, Seditious and Tumultuous Spirit, but yet ſuch I would not hate neither, but pity, and pray for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Car's peaceable Moderator, Pref.</hi> Some of the diſ-affected to the Book of Common Prayers, I take to be good Chriſtians, Honeſt, Moderate, and well meaning people, <hi>&amp;c. Item in another place.</hi> I make no Queſtion, but ſome are right honeſt Men, and truly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Conſcience, that they cannot ſubmit to ſuch Orders, and to ſuch and ſuch Rites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Testimony of above an</hi> 100 <hi>Non conformiſts for the Lawfulneſs of Lay-Communion, ſpeaking of the Nonconformiſts,</hi> thoſe <hi>good men,</hi> who met after the Plague (having preached to the People in the time of the Plague.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Dodwell<hi>'s Letters of Holy Orders.</hi> Our Conſcientious diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brethren, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 22. Their Errors themſelves are innocent to ſuch as are more intent on the improvement of Chriſtianity it ſelf, then any ſubdividing Denomination.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151109:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Stop to the Courſe of Separation, pag.</hi> 37. I will not deny, but that ſome, yea many of the Miniſters that are now laid aſide, while they had their Miniſterial ſtanding in the Pariſh Churches, and Catholick Communion, were profitable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Memorial from the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Proteſtants to his preſent Majeſty, when Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. Four of our ſucceeding Parliaments perceived the abuſe of theſe Penal Laws, and the miſchief thereby to conſcious Chriſtians, and declared there intention of relieving them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Burnet <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury <hi>on Matth.</hi> 12.25. Of the Diſſenters, who though in Errors, yet may be good men in the main, for ought we know.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Barrow<hi>'s Sermons againſt Evil Speaking.</hi> He that loveth and Reverenceth God, will acknowledge and approve his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in beſtowing gifts and graces to his Brethren; he will be afraid to diſavow, or diſgrace them, that he may not rob God himſelf of the glory due to his Favour and Mercy. <hi>Item pag.</hi> 20. God is jealous of his Glory, and therefore cannot endure it to be abuſed by ſlurring his good gifts and graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glanv. Cathol. Char. pag.</hi> 55. That our Brethren may be good men, though they underſtand not many things, in which we judge aright. <hi>Item. pag.</hi> 22. Let us then be ſo ingenuous as to own the vertue and goodneſs that is in all Parties and Opinions. Let us commend and love it. And <hi>Page</hi> 56. We ſhould converſe indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently with all perſwaſions, without wrangling or diſcord; and exerciſe our Charity and good will towards the good men of any ſort. This will be a means to ſweeten our Spirits, and to remove the Animoſities we are apt to conceive againſt the perſons of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters; and it will engage them on the other hand to a greater kindneſs for us, and ſo leſſen our diſtance and diſagreements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Ham. <hi>Catech. on Bleſſed Peace-makers.</hi> There muſt be no affixing Holineſs to Opinions, or thinking them the beſt men, that are moſt of our perſwaſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151109:15"/>
            <head>Salvation for ſuch as are Faithful in the Common Duties of Chriſtianity.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIſhop</hi> Andrew<hi>'s Sermons, Ed.</hi> 3. Such a way ſhall there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be (do all the Controverſie Writers what they can) a fair way agreed upon on all ſides, queſtioned by none, in which whoſo orders his ſteps aright, may ſee the Salvation of our God. <hi>Page</hi> 105.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon <hi>in Serm.</hi> 9. <hi>Ad aulam, Sect.</hi> 21. It may be a greater comfort to every well meaning Soul, that the ſimple belief of thoſe certain Truths, wherein all parties are in a manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, may be, and ordinarily is ſufficient for the Salvation of all thoſe, who are ſincerely careful according to that meaſure of Light and means which God hath vouchſafed them, to actuate their Faith with Piety, Charity, and good Works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailors <hi>Collection of Diſcourſe Polem. and Moral. p.</hi> 403. He takes it for granted that one Heaven ſhall hold men of ſeveral O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and the Unity of the Faith is not deſtroyed by that which men call different Religions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, p.</hi> 595. Speaking of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> they keep the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they build upon God in Jeſus Chriſt, they profeſs the Apoſtles Creed, they retain Faith and Repentance, as the ſupporters of all their hope of Heaven, and believe many more Truths than can be proved to be of ſimple and original neceſſity to Salvation; and therefore all the wiſeſt perſonages of the adverſe party allow to them poſſibility of Salvation, whilſt their Errors are not Faults of their Wills, but weakneſſes and deceptions of their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item. p.</hi> 713. Now thus much alſo your men allow to us; thoſe who Live well, and Die in a true, though but general Repentance of their Sins and Errors, even amongſt us, your beſt and wiſeſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151109:16"/> men pronounce to be in a ſaveable Condition, (ſpoken of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> Charity to us.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury<hi>'s Remarks on the Methods for Converting Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, p.</hi> 104. A Church may be a true Church (which is a Society of Men, among whom are the certain means of Salvation) and yet be corrupted with many Errors; and thus as long as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> acknowledges the Expiation and Satisfaction made by the Death of Chriſt, and applies it to all that truly believe, and amend their Lives, ſo long ſhe is a true Church; ſo that thoſe in that Communion who adhere truly to that which is the great Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental of the Chriſtian Religion, may be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Chillingſworth<hi>'s Religion of Proteſtants a ſafe way to Salvation, In his Anſwer to the Preface of Charity maintained, pag.</hi> 14. How of diſ-agreeing Proteſtants both parties may hope for Salvation: If they uſe their beſt endeavours to believe the Scripture in the true Senſe, and to live according to it, (as I hope many of all ſides do) it is impoſſible but they ſhould believe aright, and if they perform the condition of ſincere Obedience, why ſhould they not expect that God will perform his promiſe, and give them Salvation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hooker<hi>'s Diſcourſe of Juſtification, pag.</hi> 56. As many as hold the Foundation, and as it were with a ſlender Thread, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they frame many baſe and unſuitable things upon it, things that cannot abide the Trial of the Fire, yet they ſhall paſs the Fiery Trial and be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collection of Sermons of Mr.</hi> Samuel Ward <hi>of</hi> Ipſwich, <hi>pag.</hi> 18. With God, I dare be bold to ſay, there is neither <hi>Calviniſt</hi> nor <hi>Lutheran, Proteſtant</hi> nor <hi>Puritan, Conformitan</hi> or <hi>Inconformitan;</hi> but Faith and Love in Chriſt is all in all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Reynold<hi>'s Brotherly Agreement, pag.</hi> 15. Where one and the ſame ſtraight Road is kept, a ſmall difference of Paths doth not hinder Travellers from coming to the ſame Inn at Night. [Spoken with reference to the different Sects of Chriſtians who may yet in their ſeveral ways meet at the ſame Heaven.]</p>
            <p>Glanvel<hi>'s Catholick Charity, pag.</hi> 35, 36. Its very true indeed that the way to Heaven is but one; and to walk in that, is the one thing neceſſary: but then that is not this or that particular Path, but the way of an Holy Life, which may be practiſed under very different Forms of Apprehenſion and Belief: The paths may be many in this Royal Road; he that goes in the plaineſt and neareſt is in the beſt condition for pleaſure and ſafety, but another that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151109:16"/> goes about, or in a Rugged or uneven path, may come to the ſame Journeys end, though with more difficulty and danger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge</hi> Hales <hi>Diſcourſe of Religion, pag.</hi> 33. He that fears the Lord of Heaven and Earth, walks humbly before him, thankfully lays hold on the Meſſage of Redemption by Chriſt Jeſus, ſtrives to expreſs his Thankfulneſs by the ſincerity of his Obedience; if he falls in any meaſure, is reſtleſs till he hath made his peace by true Repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such a man, whether he be an <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> or <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian,</hi> or <hi>Independant,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> he hath the Life of Religion in him, and that Life acts in him, and will conform his Soul to the Image of his Saviour, and walk along with him to Eternity. The <hi>Quakers,</hi> take away their affected ſingularities, the men are as other men. Some indeed very ſober, honeſt, juſt and plain-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-men, and ſound in moſt, if not all the important Doctrines and Practices of Chriſtianity, <hi>pag.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Wilkins <hi>Sermons, pag.</hi> 63. If a man be truly Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſincere in thoſe moſt ſubſtantial Duties of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Joy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> it is not his miſtake or failing in any other leſſer things that ſhall make him uncapable of the Kingdom of God. Again in the ſame Sermon, we are not to think the worſe of others for their differences, ſo as to deſpiſe them, or cenſure ſuch perſons as to their Eſtates and Conditions, as if they were not ſincerely Religious, nor in favour with God; for though they ſhould be Erroneous and miſtaken in their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſuch things, yet if their Converſations be more juſt and righteous than ours, if more humble and peaceable, they are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to be accounted better than we are, both more acceptable of God, and approved of men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Sherlock <hi>in Religious Aſſemblies, pag.</hi> 96. Others are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized at the great variety of Religions, but if wiſe, ſeeing there is ſo much diſpute, which is the true Religion, they would uſe the greater diligence and honeſty to find it out; and hope, that God would pardon thoſe miſtakes which are meerly the Errors of their Underſtandings, when they offer unto him a pious and devout Soul; that an honeſt man who is not byaſſed by Intereſt, and does not chuſe a falſe Religion upon a Deſign, will be accepted for his Sincerity and Devotion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Patrick<hi>'s Parable of the Pilgrim, deſcribing the Safe guide to the Heavenly Jeruſalem, pag.</hi> 14. He hath Faith enough to ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151109:17"/> and Charity enough to believe, that others may be ſaved, that are not in all points juſt of his belief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Fowler<hi>'s Principles and Practices, pag.</hi> 108. Be ſo charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as to believe well of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from us, who lead good lives, are of a modeſt and peaceable deportment, and hold no Opinions, that directly oppoſe the deſign of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Dodwell <hi>in his Letters about Holy Orders.</hi> When you have reduced them to this, to practice ſuch Duties, as are by all Parties owned eſſentially Obligatory under the State of Chriſtianity (as God be praiſed) principles ſufficient for moſt of theſe are admitted by all conſiderable parties, that violate the peace of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi>) and brought them to a carefulneſs of their ways, and a tenderneſs of Conſcience, and Inquiſitiveneſs after their Duty univerſally, if you could not perſwade them to aſſent to what you ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you muſt be as Charitable in your judgment, as you believe, God will prove favourable in his Final Sentence. <hi>Pag.</hi> 19. and 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Love and Truth in two Modeſt and Peaceable Letters from a quiet Conformable Citizen of London. pag.</hi> 39. Almighty God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to live in an Age, in which contention increaſes, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity decays: And its certain, that variety of Opinions and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Religion declare difficulty to know them truly; but my Comfort is, that there is ſo much Religion without Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, as by the true Practice of what is ſo, my Soul may be ſaved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Conformists Declare that the ſeveral Sects of Proteſtants are agreed in the Main.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIſhop</hi> Jewels <hi>Defence of the Apology, pag.</hi> 740. We ſay, that we agree among our ſelves touching the whole judgment and chief ſubſtance of Chriſtian Religion, and with one Mouth, and with one Spirit do worſhip God and the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151109:17"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or, <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt his Inſtructions to his Son.</hi> We all (God be praiſed) do agree in the grounds of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrews <hi>Sermons Edit.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>And without controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie great is the miſtery of Godlineſs,</hi> &amp;c. We ſee in our days, how men languiſh about ſome points, which they would have thought to be great, and great Controverſies there be, and great Books of Controverſies about them; yet Bleſſed be God, that hath left us ſome Miſteries clear and without controverſie; this here a Miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a great one (Religion hath no greater) yet manifeſt, and <hi>in Confeſſo</hi> with all Chriſtians. A way of peace then there ſhall be in the midſt of a World of Controverſies, in which way of peace even all parts ſhall agree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> William Barlow <hi>in his Defence of the Articles of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion against</hi> Wright<hi>'s Articles.</hi> Objecting the irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable Jars between the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Puritans</hi> in the Eſſential points of Faith, <hi>Anſwereth, pag.</hi> 20. or 21. The Jars between us, though unkind, yet not in this kind, only for Ceremonies External, no points Subſtantial.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Crakanthorp <hi>in his Defenſio Eccl. Anglicanae, chap.</hi> 33. <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. Puritanum, qui Hereticus ſit, tu, opinor, in Angliâ ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem unquam conſpexiſti: cum illis, quos tu puritanos vocas, non eſt nobis de fide aut fidei Dogmatelis ulla; de Ritibus illi &amp; Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinâ Eccleſiae noſtrae contendunt; In fide conſenſus, in Ritibus ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum &amp; Diſciplinâ diſſentimus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> George Carlton<hi>'s Anſwer to</hi> Montagues <hi>Appeal, firſt Edit. pag.</hi> 5. It was then [in Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Reign] the open Confeſſion both of the Biſhops and of the <hi>Puritans</hi> that both parts embraced a mutual conſent in Doctrine, only the difference was in matters of Inconformity. <hi>Pag.</hi> 78. <hi>To that paſſage in</hi> Montagues <hi>Appeal. Pag.</hi> 28. <hi>Juſt your Puritan Doctrine.</hi> He Anſwers, A Puritan Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is a ſtrange thing, becauſe it hath been confeſſed on both ſides, that proteſtants and and puritans have held the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines without variance: What is your end in this, but to make Diviſions where there were none?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall's <hi>Apol. againſt the Browniſts Edit.</hi> 1610. <hi>Sect.</hi> 56. <hi>pag.</hi> 138. So hath their (<hi>i. e.</hi> Nonconformiſts) Moderation oppoſed ſome Appendancies, that they have both acknowledged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the ſubſtance with equal vehemence to your oppoſition.</p>
            <p>Hooker<hi>'s Eccleſ. Polity, L.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. With <hi>Rome</hi> we do not communicate, concerning ſundry her groſs and grievous abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151109:18"/> yet touching thoſe main parts of Chriſtian Truths, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they conſtantly ſtill perſiſt, we gladly acknowledge them to be of the Family of Jeſus Chriſt; and our hearty prayer to Almighty God is, that being conjoyned ſo far forth with them, they may at length (if it be his Will) ſo yield and reform themſelves, that no diſtraction remain in any thing, but that we may all with one heart and voice glorifie God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe Church we are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hierons <hi>Sermons, pag.</hi> 500. God be praiſed, the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion is on both ſides held and taught ſincerely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Sprints <hi>Caſſand. Anglicanum, Epiſt. to the Reader.</hi> In the Foundation we all agree, Time and Day will try the Hay and Stubble from the Gold and Silver, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 11, 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Vertues <hi>Plea for Peace; pag.</hi> 44. The differences among us are only in ſuperſtructures and leſs principal Truths, whileſt in the Main and Fundamental points of our Religion we have (God be thanked) a firm Concord, as may appear by the Harmony of Confeſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Featly <hi>his Roma ruens; pag.</hi> 22. Differences among us in Matters of Faith neceſſary to Salvation there are not; our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies are <hi>de Fimbriis, non de Textu,</hi> of the Lace and Fringe of Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Pygots <hi>Sermon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.26. <hi>pag.</hi> 46. When the Goſpel of Truth hath been preached amongſt us now upwards Fourſcore years, do we ſtick at <hi>Pilates</hi> Queſtion, <hi>What is Truth? John.</hi> 18.38. Beloved, for the ſubſtance of our Religion, I ſay with St. <hi>Paul; If an Angel from Heaven ſhall preach any other Goſpel,</hi> or diſcover any other [Fundamental] Truths to us, <hi>then what we have received, let him be accurſed.</hi> And if this unhappy difference be about Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Ceremonies, God grant that whilſt we are ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in contention about niceties and ſhadows we do not loſe the Subſtance.</p>
            <p>Glanvel<hi>'s Cath. Charity, pag.</hi> 2. It's very ſtrange, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhould be ſo at odds, whoſe Religion is Peace and Love, and the reaſons of whoſe Differences are ſo ſmall in proportion to the degree of their Animoſities: Our God is one, and we have the one common Saviour, we profeſs one Goſpel, and believe the ſame <hi>Creeds,</hi> we have the ſame Sacraments, and the ſame Fundamental Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and ſince we are agreed in theſe, what is there left, that is worth the heat of a Diſpute?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151109:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Stillingfleet <hi>Dean of St.</hi> Pauls <hi>Epiſt. Dedic. before the Mischief of Separation:</hi> That there is an Agreement in Doctrine and the ſubſtantial parts of Worſhip is acknowledged in our Caſe. <hi>And pag.</hi> 13. The people apprehend the differences to be much greater than the Teachers will allow, when they are put to declare their Minds; and our common Enemies take as much advantages from our differences, as if they were really far greater than they are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformiſts Plea for the Non conformiſts, Part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 75. Indeed the Separation with which the Nonconformiſts are charged is not as Separation from a Church, but as Separation in a Church, fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally and eſſentially the ſame, but differing in Modes and Accidents, which muſt needs be the loweſt kind of difference; For the Conformiſts and Non-conformiſts are all one in Chriſt, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all the parts of <hi>Chriſtian Catholick Communion</hi> with us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Kidder<hi>'s Serm. on</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. The things in which we all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, theſe things are many, and of great weight; what we differ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout bears no proportion to thoſe things, which we are agreed in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hancock<hi>'s Sermon on Luk.</hi> 19.42. <hi>pag.</hi> 24, 25. The Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of our Luſt and Paſſion, living a life of Spiritual Purity, and Devotion, Self-denial and Meekneſs, Juſtice and Charity, Peaceableneſs and Patience, Sobriety and Chaſtity, and a truſting in the Merits of Chriſt for pardon of our Sins, and acceptance of our imperfect Righteouſneſs, theſe are the ſubſtantials of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, about which all wiſe and good men are Agreed, however we differ about other Matters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Difference of Caſe between Separation of Proteſtants from</hi> Rome, <hi>and the Separation of Diſſenters, pag.</hi> 69. As for the Diſſenters, methinks it ſhould not be hard to diſſwade the moſt of them from breaking the Communion of the Church, any longer with which they agree in the Subſtance of Faith and Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Wake<hi>'s Sermon on Rom.</hi> 15.5, 6, 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 16, 17. Our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences do not at all concern the Foundations either of Faith or Worſhip; and are therefore ſuch in which good men, if they be otherwiſe diligent and ſincere in their enquiry, may differ without any prejudice to themſelves, or any juſt reflection upon the truth of their common profeſſion.</p>
            <p>To conclude this Head. <hi>Biſh.</hi> Reynold's <hi>Br. Reconcil. p.</hi> 7. Why ſhould not the many Truths wherein we agree teach us to join in Love, which is a Chriſtian Duty, rather than the few opinions in which we diſ-agree cauſe breach in affection, which at beſt is but an human Infirmity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151109:19"/>
            <head>That the Creed contains all Truths neceſſary to Salvation.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the Common Prayer at the Viſitation of the Sick,</hi> the Miniſter by the Churches order, ſaith thus to the Sick; I ſhall rehearſe to you the Articles of our Chriſtian Faith, that you may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you do beleive as a Chriſtian man ſhould or no. And <hi>ſo Biſhop Tailor on the Credenda in the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> The Creed, which whoſoever beleives, is a Catholick and a Chriſtian; but he that beleiveth it not is neither. <hi>In Baptiſm according to the Church of England,</hi> The queſtion put to the perſon to be baptized, doſt thou beleive in God the Father? and ſo to the end of the Creed: And will thou be Baptized into this Faith? And in <hi>the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm,</hi> That in our Vow at Baptiſm we promiſed to believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith; And in <hi>the beginning of the Reformation,</hi> it was agreed upon, that the Biſhops and Preachers ought to inſtruct the people according to the Scripture, the Three Creeds, and the four firſt General Councels. The Fathers are cited by the Reverend Biſhops in teſtimony that the Creed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all Truths neceſſary to Salvation; as by <hi>Arch-Biſhop Laud, againſt Fiſher, Biſhop Taylors Ductor Dub.</hi> and <hi>Biſhop Bramhal</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Tertullian, Clemens Romanus, Ambroſe, Auguſtine,</hi> &amp;c. who made the Creed to be the only ſtanding immoveable, and irreform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Rule of Faith; the ſum of the whole Catholick Faith; the Key of the Chriſtian Faith; the rule and ſquare of the Apoſtical Sermons, (<hi>i. e.</hi> after the making of it;) wherein the Apoſtles have collected into one breviary all the points of the Catholick Faith, which are diffuſed throughout all the Scriptures. The Creed is one perfect collection and ſum, plain, ſhort and full, that the plainneſs might help the weakneſs of the Hearers, the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs their Memory, the Fulneſs their Inſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151109:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The General Councel of Epheſus,</hi> did forbid all men to exact any more of a Chriſtian at his Baptiſmal profeſſion: and <hi>again the ſame Councel,</hi> That it ſhould be lawful for no man to publiſh or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe another Faith or Creed, then that which was defined by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councel, and that whoſoever ſhould dare to compoſe, or offer any ſuch to any perſons willing to be converted from Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, Judaiſm, or Hereſie, if they ſhould be Biſhops, or Clergy-men, ſhould be depoſed; if Lay-men, Anathematiſed, <hi>i. e.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed with Excommunication. It was the Univerſal practice of the Primitive Church, <hi>Crediſne</hi> at Baptiſm? On Palm-Sunday, the Chriſtian converts from Heatheniſm, as yet under Catechizing, petitioned for Baptiſm; and from that day forward had ſome aſſigned to expound the Creed unto them, whereof they were to make ſolemn profeſſion at Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the Divines of the Reformed Church</hi> confeſſedly and generally own this Truth, that the Creed contains all Truths neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Halls <hi>Works, p.</hi> 637. 'Tis not <hi>Caſſander</hi>'s Speech only, but every wiſe and honeſt man's, the Creed is the common cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of our Faith; ſurely, ſaith he, <hi>Theodoret,</hi> when he would allay the bitter contentions of thoſe antient Chriſtians of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och, writes thus,</hi> both parts made one and the ſame confeſſion of their Faith; for both maintained the Creed of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and blames the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> that the confeſſion of the ſame Creed is not ſufficient with them for peace. <hi>Item Reſolution of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Caſes of Conſcience, Caſe</hi> 5. <hi>Dec.</hi> 3 <hi>d.</hi> If there were not ſome ſpecial Truths, the belief whereof makes and diſtinguiſhes a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the authors of the Creed Apoſtolick, beſides the other ſymbols received anciently in the Church, were much deceived in their aim.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Potters <hi>Anſwer to Charity Miſtaken, p.</hi> 221. How can it be neceſſary for any Chriſtian to have more in his Creed, than the Apoſtles had in the Church of their time; may the Church of after ages make the way to Heaven narrower, than our Saviour left it, &amp;c. The Apoſtles profeſs, they revealed to the Church the whole Councel of God, keeping back nothing needful for our Salvation; What Tyranny then is it to impoſe any new matters on the Faith of Chriſtians, eſpecially as the late Popes have done, under that high commanding Form, <hi>Qui non crediderit, aut fecerit, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151109:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor <hi>Coll. of Diſcourſes, p.</hi> 524. It is a ſtrange Boldneſs in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> firſt to add Twelve new Articles to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creed, and then to add the appendix of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> this is the Catholick Faith, without which no man can be ſaved. For I demand, can any man ſay and juſtifie, that the Apoſtles did deny Communion to any man, that believed the Apoſtles Creed, and lived a good Life? Let them remember Pope <hi>Pelagius,</hi> who when the Biſhops of <hi>Iſtria</hi> deſerted his Communion <hi>in cauſa trium Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulorum,</hi> he gave them an account of his Faith by recitation of the Creed, and by atteſting the Four General Councels, and is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent upon this, that <hi>de fidei firmitate nulla poterit eſſe queſtio, vel ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicio generari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Uſher, <hi>In thoſe Propoſitions,</hi> which without all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie are univerſally received in the whole Chriſtian World, <hi>[i. e. Articles of the Creed]</hi> ſo much Truth is contained as being joyned with an holy obedience, may be ſufficient to bring a man unto Everlaſting Salvation; and that as many as walk according to this Rule, peace ſhall be upon them. Upon which ſaith <hi>Doctor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingworth,</hi> this is a great and as good a Truth, and as neceſſary for theſe miſerable Times, as can be uttered.</p>
            <p>Hookers <hi>Eccleſ. Polit. p.</hi> 266. We have received from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt that brief confeſſion of Faith, which hath been always a badge of the Church, a mark whereby to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Chriſtian men from Infidels and Jews.</p>
            <p>Dr. Hammond <hi>of Schiſm, p.</hi> 58. Calls the Creed the Apoſtolick badge or mark, <hi>A teſſera</hi> or token of the Apoſtles having planted the Faith in any Church, the known ſummary of that beleif which had been received from the Apoſtles, <hi>p.</hi> 211. It cannot be affirmed of all the Articles of the Creed, that they are thus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary, (<hi>i. e.</hi> that no man can be imagined to Reform his Life, ſo as to be acceptable to God, but he to whom every one of thoſe Articles has been intelligibly revealed;) for as to many plain yet pious Chriſtians, its not certain that can be affirmed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor <hi>Coll of diſc. p.</hi> 536. The Religion of Jeſus Chriſt is the Form of ſound Doctrine, ſet down in Scripture, ſeparated as to the Queſtion of neceſſary, or not neceſſary, by the ſymbol of the Apoſtles. <hi>Item</hi> p. 407. Now if more were neceſſary than the Articles of the Creed, I demand, why was it made the characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtick note of a Chriſtian from an Heretick, Jew or an Infidel? or to what purpoſe was it compoſed? or if this were intended as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151109:20"/> ſufficient, did the Apoſtles or thoſe Churches which they found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed know any thing elſe to be neceſſary?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Sparrows <hi>Rationale upon the Common Prayer, p.</hi> 50. In the time of the ſtay at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they agreed upon this Creed as a Rule of Faith, according to the Analogy of which they and all others ſhould teach; and as a word of diſtinction, by which they ſhould know Friend from Foes; for as the <hi>Gileadits</hi> by the word <hi>Shibboleth, Judges</hi> 12. 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So the Apoſtles and the Church ſhould know who were right believers, who falſe, by this word of Faith: for all that walked according to this Rule, and Profeſſed this Faith, ſhe acknowledged for hers, and gave them her peace; but all others that went contrary to this Rule and Word, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted enemies, <hi>(Tertull. de praeſcriptione)</hi> and lead by falſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6. <hi>Item,</hi> a Chriſtian evidences to the Church his ſound beleif, by expreſly repeating the Creed, and every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thereof, which is, and always hath been accounted the mark and character, whereby to diſtinguiſh a true beleiver from an Heretick or Infidel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge</hi> Hales <hi>diſcourſe of Religion, p.</hi> 4. The <hi>Credenda</hi> or things to be known, or beleived, are but few, and intelligible, briefly delivered in that ſummary of Chriſtian Religion, uſually called the Apoſtles Creed; and in brief the Baptiſmal Covenant, as it is contained in the Liturgy, and Explanation thereof in the Church Catechiſm, [<hi>i. e.</hi> by the Covenant Mercies and Covenant-duties] together with the precepts of the Decalogue, contain in effect the ſummary, or brief Epitome of our Chriſtian duty.</p>
            <p>Cars <hi>peaceable Moder. p.</hi> 43. The Creed is a ſhort Abridgment and Epitome of the Apoſtles Doctrine which they received from Chriſt our Saviour, and delivered to us in the New Teſtament, the Rule of our Faith, Touch-ſtone of Truth, the pith and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our Chriſtian Religion, the very badge and cognizance of a Chriſtian, whereby he is not only known from Pagans, but alſo diſtinguiſhed from Hereticks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Pearſon, <hi>The Creed</hi> without controverſie is a brief com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the objects of our Chriſtian Faith, and is generally taken to contain all things neceſſary to be beleived, <hi>in praef. to his Expoſition on the Apostles Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Glanvell's <hi>Catholick Charity p.</hi> 30. The Fundamentals of belief are few and plain; for certainly the Divine goodneſs would not lay our Eternal intereſt in difficulties and multitudes, things
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151109:21"/> hard to be underſtood, and retain'd. <hi>Item, Agreement of Reaſon and Religion, pag.</hi> 5. In the <hi>Creed</hi> are all the Fundamentals of Religion, and though our Church require our Aſſent (Miniſters he means) to more propoſitions, yet thoſe are only <hi>Articles</hi> of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, not <hi>Doctrines</hi> abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation: And if we go beyond the <hi>Creed</hi> for Eſſentials of Faith, who can tell where we ſhall ſtop?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Tillotſon. I doubt not, but that the belief of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Creed,</hi> provided we entertain nothing, that is deſtructive of it, together with a good Life will certainly ſave a Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True ſtate of the Primitive Church; Part Firſt.</hi> That which we commonly call the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> if it were not compoſed by them, yet certainly by Primitive and Apoſtolick men, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as the ſum of Chriſtian Faith, the ſum total neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. It cannot be ſuppoſed, that they left out any thing which they thought neceſſary to Salvation; they might as well have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted half, or all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Steward<hi>'s Englands Caſe, pag.</hi> 20. In our Reformation we ſtill adhering unto the Three <hi>Creeds,</hi> which are the Faith of the <hi>Church Catholick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hancock<hi>'s Sermon on Luk.</hi> 19.42. <hi>pag.</hi> 26. To the Honour of the Church of <hi>England</hi> let it be ſaid, whatſoever is impoſed on us as neceſſary to the Salvation of all men, is contained in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>Creed.</hi> This is the Faith of the firſt and beſt times of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; the Faith into which we are Baptized, and the Belief of this <hi>Creed</hi> hath a direct influence on our Chriſtian practice, which is the great buſineſs of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Sanderſon <hi>in his nine Caſes of Conſcience, pag</hi> 8. Whoſoever well conſiders, may reſt ſatisfied in his judgment and conſcience, that the Faith profeſſed and taught in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is a plain and ſafe way to lead a Chriſtian Believer to Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if he withal lead his life and converſation anſwerable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Barrow<hi>'s Diſcourſe of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church annexed to his Treatiſe againſt the Popes Supremacy.</hi> In regard to this Union of Faith, among Chriſtians, the Body of Chriſtians adhering to it, was called the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> from which all thoſe were eſteemed <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> to be cut off and ſeparated, who in any point deſerted that Faith, <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:151109:21"/>
            <head>Conformiſts not forward in Cenſuring any as guilty of Heretical and Damnable Errors.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HOmily of Contention, Firſt Part.</hi> May help with other Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to explain the Hereticalneſs of an Error. He that is faulty let him rather amend, than defend that which he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a miſs, leaſt he fall by contention from a fooliſh Error into an obſtinate Hereſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewel's <hi>Def. of Apol. pag.</hi> 46. For juſt proof of Hereſie three things neceſſarily be required. 1. That it be an Error. 2. That it be an Error againſt the Truth of Gods Word; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe every Error maketh not an Hereſie. 3. That it be ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wilfully maintained; otherwiſe an Error in Gods Truth without wilful maintainance is not an Hereſie. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Errare poſſum Hereticus eſſe non poſſum. Item p.</hi> 67. The Catholick Fathers and Biſhops made no doubt but our Religion might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of the Scriptures; neither were they ever ſo hardy to take any for an Heretick, whoſe Error could not evidently and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently be reproved by the ſelf-ſame Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrews <hi>cited in Appendix to the third Part of the Friendly Debate.</hi> Let but obſtinacy and perverſeneſs be wanting, it will be no Hereſie; and if it be Hereſie, being about a point not of Faith but of Diſcipline, [whether Epiſcopacy be a diſtinct order from Presbitery] it will not be among thoſe things which St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>Damnable Hereſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall<hi>'s Reſolutions of divers Caſes of Conſcience, Dec.</hi> 3. <hi>Caſe</hi> 5. Whoſoever ſhall wilfully impugne any of the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, refuſe to acknowledge and receive the Sacraments expreſly inſtituted by Chriſt, comes within the verge of Hereſie: Wilfully I ſay; for meer Error makes not an Hereſie; If out of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151109:22"/> ſimplicity, or groſs Ignorance a man ſhall take upon him to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a contradiction to a point of Faith, being ready to repent upon better light, he may not be thus Branded: Eviction and Contumacy muſt improve his Error to be Heretical.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bramhall<hi>'s Juſt Vindication of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 26. A man may render himſelf guilty of Heretical pravity, 1. By diſ-believing any Fundamental Article of Faith, and neceſſary part of ſaving Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. By believing any Superſtitious Errors or Additions, which do vertually and by neceſſary and evident conſequences ſubvert the Faith, and overthrow fundamental Truths. 3. By maintaining leſſer Errors obſtinately after ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Conviction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But becauſe that conſequence, which ſeems clear and neceſſary to one man, may ſeem weak to another; and becauſe we cannot penetrate into the hearts of men, to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be obſtinate, or do implicitely and in the preparation of their Mind believe the Truth, its good to be ſparing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Cenſuring Hereticks for Obſtinacy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor<hi>'s Collection of Diſcourſes, pag.</hi> 117. When I reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Obſtinacy among thoſe things which make a falſe opinion Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, there is an obſtinacy of the will, which is indeed highly guilty of Miſ-demeanor; and when the School makes pertinacy or obſtinacy to be the Formality of Hereſie they ſay not true at all, unleſs it be meant the obſtinacy of the Will, or Choice. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dequate and perfect formality of Hereſie is whatſoever makes the Error voluntary or vitious, as is clear in Scripture, reckoning Covetouſneſs, Pride, and Luſt, and whatſoever is vitious to be its cauſes: but there is alſo an Obſtinacy (you may call it) but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, is nothing but a reſolution and a confirmation of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which is not in a mans power honeſtly to alter; and it is not all the commands of Humanity, that can be Arguments ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make a man leave believing that for which he thinks he hath reaſon, for which he hath ſuch Arguments as heartily convince him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item. pag.</hi> 417. It is very hard to be diſcerned, becauſe thoſe accidental and Inherent Crimes, which make a man an Heretick in Queſtions not ſimply Fundamental, or of neceſſary practice, are actions ſo Internal, and Spiritual, that cognizance can but ſeldom be taken of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> William<hi>'s Truth, pag.</hi> 32. Becauſe is is a ſin ſo fearful to perſiſt maliciouſly and obſtinately in a known Hereſie, and becauſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151109:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> of mine own Ignorance of Mens hearts what their thoughts be, how far their knowledge reacheth, or how much their Malice pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth with them, I dare not be ſo bold as in my thoughts to lay a ſin ſo grievous to any mans Charge.</p>
            <p>Glanvil<hi>'s Cath. Charity.</hi> Its very true, that Error many times is occaſioned by a corrupt Byas in the Will and Affections: but then, if our Erring Brother be ſincere in other matters, we are not to conclude, that his underſtanding is this way corrupted, and we can ſcarce be certain of it in any caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſign of Chriſtianity, pag.</hi> 232. Would we know whether we Embrace all the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity, and are guilty of no Damnable and Deſtructive Errors? Examine we our ſelves, are we ſincerely willing to obey in all things commanded, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily endeavour to have a right underſtanding of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in order to the bettering of our Souls by the Doctrines, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> This obedient temper is the moſt infallible mark of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox man; ſuch an one though he may err, cannot be an Heretick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond <hi>of Schiſm, pag.</hi> 24. How light and inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (and extrinſecal to the Foundation) ſoever the Error may be ſuppoſed to be; yet if there be Obſtinacy in the continuing in it againſt light and conviction, this certainly is a ſin, neither light, nor inconſiderable, nor reconcileable with Chriſtian Practice.</p>
            <p>Hooker<hi>'s Diſcourſe of Juſtification, pag.</hi> 43. Many are partakers of the Error, which are not of the Hereſie of the Church of <hi>Rome. Put a difference,</hi> [ſaith St. <hi>Jude] have compaſſion upon ſome.</hi> Shall we lay up all in one Condition? Shall we caſt them all headlong? Shall we plunge them all into that infernal Everlaſting Flaming Lake? Them that have been partakers of the Errors of <hi>Babylon</hi> together with them which are in <hi>Hereſie?</hi> Them that have been Authours of <hi>Hereſie</hi> with them that by Terror and Violence have been forced to receive it? They who have Taught it, with them whoſe ſimplicity hath by ſleight and conveyances of falſe Teachers been ſeduced to believe it? Them which have been partakers in one, with them which have been partakers in many? Them which in many, with them which in all?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item pag.</hi> 64. Conſidering how many Vertuous and juſt men, how many Saints, how many Martyrs, how many Ancient Fathers of the Church have had their ſundry perilous opinions, (and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>Errare poſſum, Hereticus eſſe nolo,</hi> except
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151109:23"/> we put a difference between them that Err, and obſtinately perſiſt in Error, how is it poſſible that ever any man ſhould hope to be ſaved?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Chillingworth <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. The intended ſence of Scripture is not ſo fully declared in points not neceſſary, but that they which oppoſe it, may verily believe, that they indeed main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, and have great ſhew of Reaſon to induce them to believe ſo; and therefore are not to be Damned, as men oppoſing that which they know to be a Truth delivered in Scripture, or have no probable Reaſons to believe the contrary; but rather in Charity to be acquitted and abſolved, as men, who endeavour to find the Truth, but fail of it, through Humane Frailty. <hi>Item chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 19. He oppoſeth not that, which he doth know to be true, but only that you know to be ſo, and which he might know, were he void of prejudice, which is a Fault, I confeſs, but a fault incident to good and honeſt men very often.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>That none are to be ſhut out of the Church, and denied Communion for Leſſer Sins and Errors.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIſhop</hi> Tailors <hi>Ductor Dubitantium.</hi> In what caſe is Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to be inflicted? I chuſe to give it in the words of the Fathers, becauſe there is in this caſe Reaſon and Authority too. 1. Unleſs the offence be evident, no man muſt be excommunicated, ſays <hi>Origen</hi> [agreeably <hi>Hooker Eccl. Pol. pag.</hi> 408. As for Iniquity and Sin, it lieth many times hid; and becauſe we be all offenders, it becometh us, not to encline towards hard and ſevere ſentences touching others, unleſs upon notorious wickedneſs.] 2. None but <hi>peccator gravis &amp; ſcandaloſus:</hi> Why ſhould a man proceed to violent remedies, when a gentle application will make the cure? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fathers in the <hi>Council of Worms in Can.</hi> 2. Decreed; <hi>Nullus Sacerdotum, &amp;c.</hi> no Prieſt ſhall excommunicate any man ſound in the Faith, for ſmall and light cauſes, but only for ſome very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous fault, according to the practice of the Fathers. St. <hi>Leo</hi> in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151109:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> the 93. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> forbade, Let not the Communion be eaſily or lightly denied to any Chriſtian, nor at the pleaſure of every angry Prieſt. It was a worthy cauſe of complaint in St. <hi>Leo,</hi> to conſider, that this evil was done for ſo little things; and therefore if the Church do Excommunicate him, whoſe Actions or Words though faulty, yet can conſiſt with the ſtate of a good man, and do not deſtroy the Love of God, the Cenſure was too heavy as to the External, and falſe as to the Internal Communion. For the man is not fallen from God, but doth communicate with the head, and continue to receive of the Spirit of Chriſt. 3. Neither is this ſufficient; a ſcandalous ſin alone is not enough: for Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is the laſt remedy: <hi>Omnia prius tentanda.</hi> When nothing elſe will do it, then is this to be uſed for his amendment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Uſher<hi>'s Directions concerning Liturgy; and Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> That none might be excommunicated but by the Biſhop himſelf, with the conſent of the Paſtor, in thoſe Pariſhes the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent dwells; and that for heinous and ſcandalous Crimes, joyned with obſtinacy and wilful contempt. <hi>Idem In his Body of Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Pearſon <hi>on the Creed, pag.</hi> 350. By great and ſcandalous offences, by incorrigible miſ-demeanors we my incur the Cenſure of the Church of God; and while we are ſhut out thence, we ſtand excluded out of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item Doctor</hi> More<hi>'s Miſtery of Godlineſs,</hi> 14. <hi>chap.</hi> That none are to be excluded from Communion that profeſs the belief of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, and the Creed, unleſs they ſtand guilty for ſome groſs and ſcandalous ſins, and do perſiſt therein impenitent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reclaim'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, The Judgment of the Church</hi> being nothing elſe, but an effective and terrible Declaration of the Judgment of God, muſt not be exterminating and Final, for things of little concernment, but according to the Mercy which we hope for: Again, If the Church kills on Earth (<hi>i. e.</hi> Excommunicates) and God ſaves in Heaven, its clear, ſhe hath not uſed her power aright; Whoever deſerves Excommunication, deſerves Damnation, <hi>pag.</hi> 530. <hi>in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Diſcourſe Polemical and Moral.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Commination.</hi> The perſons coming under the Diſcipline of the Church, <hi>ſaid to be ſuch,</hi> as ſtood convict of Notorious Sin. <hi>And further,</hi> the Wrath of God which obſtinate ſinners through the ſtubbornneſs of their Hearts have heaped unto themſelves, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151109:24"/> deſpiſed the Goodneſs, Patience, and Long-ſufferance of God, when he called them continually to Repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>Curſes therein are denounced</hi> againſt wilful and open Evil-Livers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Article</hi> 33. <hi>of the Church of</hi> England. That perſon, which by open denunciation of the Church, is rightly cut off that is Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On which Mr. <hi>Rogers Expoſition</hi> reckons two ſorts of men to be rightly Excommunicated, whereof the one pervert the ſound Doctrine of the Truth, as did <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> the Reſurrection; the other ſort, ſuch as be defiled with notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewel<hi>'s Defence of the Apol. pag.</hi> 140. The Miniſter, we ſay, ſhutteth up the gate of the Kingdom of Heaven againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing and ſtubborn perſons, denouncing unto them Gods Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance and Everlaſting puniſhment; or elſe quite ſhutting them out of the Boſom of the Church by open Excommunication.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item pag.</hi> 146. That the wicked and wilful, and ſuch as would not believe, <hi>&amp;c. Item. Reply to</hi> Harding, <hi>pag.</hi> 32. Perſons Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate upon great and notorious Crimes could not be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to communicate with the reſt of the Faithful. <hi>Item. pag.</hi> 88. The apparent wicked and ungodly were removed from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrew<hi>'s Latter Sermons, pag.</hi> 32. It hath ever been held good Divinity that the Church from Chriſt received power to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and ſeparate wilful offenders. <hi>Item pag.</hi> 55. Speaking of the ſame power given to Edification and not to Deſtruction, I ſay not firſt and principally to Deſtruction, nor of any ſave only of the wilful and impenitent Sinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item Biſhop</hi> Andrew<hi>'s Sermons, Edit.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 727. Then is not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Error repugnant to Gods Grace. God is able to pardon, and not impute Error in Opinion, as well as Error in Practice; did not the High Prieſt offer as well for the Errors, as the Tranſgreſſions of the people? This only we are to look to, that with St. <hi>Peter</hi> we be not wilful; if there come a clear <hi>comperi</hi> as ready to relent in the one, as to repent of the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> Laud <hi>cited in Dr.</hi> Puller<hi>'s Moderation of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 391. The Church of <hi>England</hi> is not ſuch a ſhrew to her children, as to deny her Bleſſing, or denounce an <hi>Anathema</hi> againſt them, if ſome peaceably diſſent in Points remoter from the Foundation.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151109:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Davenant<hi>'s Letter to</hi> Duraeus. The Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> ſaith he, and the Articles therein contained he that believeth, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to lead a Life conformable to the commands of Chriſt, is not to be blotted out of the Roul of Chriſtians, nor expelled from Communion with other Members of any Chriſtian Church whatſoever, <hi>Item.</hi> That Church doth too much pleaſe it ſelf, which rejects others (in which neither Tyranny, nor Idolatry, nor Deadly Hereſie is found) as men unworthy of Communion with her, for ſome Infirmity of Underſtanding: the Fathers of the Ancient Church did not ſo.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould men be more rigid than God? Why ſhould any Error exclude any man from the Churches communion, which will not deprive him of Eternal Salvation? <hi>Dr.</hi> Chill. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 40. <hi>of his Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Chillingw. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. What Man or Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the <hi>Creed,</hi> and all the evident conſequences of it, if alſo he believe the Scripture ſincerely and heartily, cannot poſſibly be in any Error of ſimple belief offenſive unto God, nor deſerve for any ſuch Error to be deprived of his Life, or cut off from the Churches communion, and hope of Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir</hi> Francis Bacon. In his Advertiſement of the controverſies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of his works, <hi>pag.</hi> 138. <hi>pag.</hi> 192. Of the abuſe of Excommunication, <hi>vide</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hooker<hi>'s Diſcourſe of Juſtification, pag.</hi> 54. If was a perilous Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror that the <hi>Galatians</hi> held about Juſtification, yet ſo far was St. <hi>Paul</hi> from ſtriking their Names out of Chriſt's Book, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth others to receive them [<hi>i. e.</hi> to have communion with them] with ſingular Humanity, uſe them as Brethren: he knew mans imbecility, had a feeling of our blindneſs, which are Mortal Men, how great it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Judgment of the Profeſſors of Divinity in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen, <hi>mentioned pag.</hi> 707, <hi>is not unſuitable to this Subject.</hi> That the condition of that Church is worſe, and incomparably more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, that is ſo ſwelled and puft up with the ſplendour of its Golden Edifice upon the Foundation, or of its Orthodoxy, that neglecting Charity and Equanimity, and trampling on the Law of Chriſt, faſtidiouſly rejects, and Anathematizeth other Churches, Orthodox in the Foundation, and willing to maintain place with it, than is the condition of thoſe Churches, who, though they are infirm in Faith, inferiour in knowledge, do yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151109:25"/> hold in the Foundation, maintain inviolable Charity, and after the Example of Bleſſed <hi>Cyprian,</hi> do neither judge nor ſeparate from Communion, thoſe who think otherwiſe than themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Caſaubon<hi>'s Neceſſity of Reformation, pag.</hi> 142. <hi>cited by Dr.</hi> Puller<hi>'s Moderation</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 436. Were there nothing elſe object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Papiſts</hi> but this one thing, their uncharitable proſcribing and Excommunicating all Chriſtians, in all parts of the World [as in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> impoſing her Doctrines which were but diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table before, to be <hi>de fide,</hi> with an <hi>Anathema</hi> to ſuch as thought of them otherwiſe] who are not of their Communion, and oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that adhere unto them to profeſs the ſame; I ſhould think <hi>that one thing</hi> a juſt ground of Separation or forſaking their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Steward<hi>'s Englands Caſe, pag.</hi> 26. When Men caſt out of the Church Catholick, and ſo damn to Hell all thoſe that hold not their Opinions; this St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> oft-times calls Schiſm in the <hi>Donatiſts:</hi> I could name you thoſe who are guilty of this; but I am ſure, our dear Mother is not, who hath been ſo mild to thoſe who have moſt highly oppoſed her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond's <hi>Pract. Catech. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Bleſſed are the Peace-makers.</hi> We are not to think our own Opinions in Religion, ſuch as are not of Faith, of ſuch importance, as to deny Communion or Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to thoſe who differ from us. <hi>Item of Schiſm, pag.</hi> 165. and <hi>pag.</hi> 166. That as we exclude no Chriſtian from our Communion, that will either Filially and Fraternally embrace it with us, being ready to admit any to our Aſſemblies, that acknowledge the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation laid by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; ſo we as earneſtly deſire to be admitted to the like Freedom of External Communion with all the Members of all other Chriſtian Churches, as often as occaſion makes us capable of that Bleſſing. And <hi>pag.</hi> 5. Tell us, the Governours of the Church uſe to inflict that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Excommunication on the moſt ſcandalous Sinner. And <hi>pag.</hi> 15. Calls it that very condition into which the Adulterer and obſtinate offender is caſt by the Cenſures of the Church.</p>
            <p>Hammond <hi>of the Keys, chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. The more ſhame for the over-eaſie denouncers of that cenſure, that inflict it for every tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial commiſſion, without conſideration whether or no repented of; or that uſe this Sovereign <hi>Recipe</hi> unadviſedly for any other end than Reforming the Profane.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151109:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Puller<hi>'s Moderation of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 366. It is evident that the Divine Moderation of our Church conſiders the frame of Man, and the uncertainty, difficulty, and imperfection of Humane Knowledge, the weakneſs and variety of Humane Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, ſhe alloweth much to the force of Prejudice, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the power and artifice of Seducers: Our Church makes a great reſerve of Diſpenſation to perſons of Modeſt, Humble, Docible, and peaceable Spirits, and proportions her Cenſures to the degrees of Malice, and the Unchriſtian Temper which appears in Offenders.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Cumber <hi>on the Common-Prayer in the Commination.</hi> Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline with-held in favour of Diſſenters, leaſt the impoſing it there ſhould make this Holy Means of Reformation deſpiſed rather than obeyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item pag.</hi> 369. <hi>Dr.</hi> Puller. Wherefore the Inſtitution of a Chriſtian Man [made by <hi>Cranmer</hi>] ſaith, the Biſhops are not bound ſo preciſely, but they may attemper and forbear the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Juriſdiction, when by ſo doing the cure of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and the tranquility of the Church may be furthered. <hi>Item pag.</hi> 35. According to Equity our Church deſires all her Laws may be Interpreted; <hi>Benignius Leges interpretandae ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> She ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of a Mitigation of a rigid Sentence. <hi>And pag.</hi> 11. Diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, where the Laws preſs too hard upon particular perſons, to relax the Rigour of them. <hi>Pag.</hi> 370. Wherefore thoſe who in Execution of the Church Diſcipline, abuſe the moſt excellent Temper of the Church, in the conſtitution of her Laws, under the pretence of Eccleſiaſtical Authority, verily, they moſt of all deſerve the Churches Rod, and the dire point of her <hi>Anathema.</hi> Let it be conſidered, ſaid <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor, <hi>Ductor Dub. L.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 259. How Great a reproach it is to Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline, if it be made to Miniſter to Covetouſneſs, and to the needs of Proctors and Advocates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bramhall, <hi>pag.</hi> 14. <hi>Vindicat. of the Church.</hi> To exclude none from Catholick communion and hope of Salvation, either Eaſtern, or Weſtern, or Southern, or Northern Chriſtians which profeſs the Faith of the Apoſtles and Primitive Fathers eſtabliſhed in the firſt General Councils, and comprehended in the <hi>Apoſtolick, Nicene,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian Creeds,</hi> and laſtly to hold an Actual Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Communion with them <hi>in votis,</hi> in our deſires, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it by all lawful means. <hi>Item, pag.</hi> 17. There is not the like
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151109:26"/> neceſſity of communicating in all Externals, there is not ſo great conformity to be expected in ceremonies as in the Eſſentials of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bilſon <hi>of Subjection, Part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 223. <hi>Edit.</hi> 4. It is a moſt pernitious fancy to think that divers Nations and Countries differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Cuſtoms, Laws, and Manners (ſo they hold one and the ſame Rule of Faith in the Bond of Peace) cannot be parts of the Catholick Church, Communicant one with another. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints ſtandeth not in External Rights, Cuſtoms, and Manners; but in believing the ſame truth, taſting of the ſame grace, reſting on the ſame Hope, calling on the ſame God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in the ſame Spirit, whereby they be ſealed, ſanctified, and preſerved unto the day of Redemption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cauſes of Decay of Chriſtian Piety, pag.</hi> 285. As Chriſt, when he forewarned his Diſciples of the enſuing perſecution, tells them not only, they ſhould be killed, but they ſhould be put out of the Synagogue; ſo now, as if Chriſtians were emulous of every branch of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cruelty, we tranſcribe that part of the Copy too, and either by cauſeleſs Excommunicating others, or ſeparating our ſelves, we deny the benefit of Publick Communion to each other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, pag.</hi> 280. <hi>Every Petty difference, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 287. Would we indeed comport with the Example of thoſe happy Times <hi>[of the Primitive Church]</hi> we ſhould have prayed for the Converſion of Diſſenters, not laid <hi>Anathema</hi>'s upon them, and prayed for their confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, In his whole Duty of Man:</hi> If one that holds all neceſſary Chriſtian Truths happen yet to be in ſome Error, we are not for this to deſpiſe his Perſon, or forſake his Communion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Reynold<hi>'s Brotherly Agreement.</hi> In the caſe of unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Differences amongſt good Men, there ought to be mutual Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not to judge, deſpiſe, reject, inſult over one another, not to deal with the weaker as Aliens, but as Brethren; not to proceed preſently unto Separation, Rejection, Anathematization; but to reſtore thoſe that are overtaken with an Error, in the ſpirit of Meekneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Aleſtry, <hi>Serm.</hi> 9. <hi>pag.</hi> 170. <hi>Cenſuring the abuſe of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</hi> If they be not ſo happy as to be Orthodox, ſending them down to Hell directly.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151109:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Barrow, <hi>In his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church, Speaking of the Roman Churches.</hi> If Churches do maintain impious Errors, if they do preſcribe naughty practices, if they do reject communion and peace upon reaſonable Tearms, if they vent unjuſt and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If they damn, and perſecute all that refuſe to be their Subjects in ſuch caſes we may Reject ſuch Churches as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, or Schiſmatical, or wickedly uncharitable, and unjuſt in their proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> More <hi>in his Pref. to the Miſtery of Godlineſs, pag.</hi> 19 The Object of Church diſcipline ought to contain nothing but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable Truths of our Religion, namely the generally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and plain indiſpenſable Duties of Life, for theſe are ſuch, as deſerve to be held up with all poſſible care and ſtrictneſs: Other things ſo gently recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that no conſcientious man may be pinched by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Stillingfleet<hi>'s Preface to Irenicum.</hi> What poſſible Reaſon can be aſſigned, why ſuch things ſhould not be ſufficient for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with a Church, which are ſufficient for Eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And certainly thoſe things are ſufficient for that, which are laid down as neceſſary Duty's of Chriſtianity by our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in his Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Cave<hi>'s Goſpel preached to the Romans, Serm.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 89. God be thanked, ſuch is the preſent Moderation of our Churches Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical conſtitutions, our penalties are not for Deſtruction, but for correction and amendment; we puniſh none for their bare opinions, and readily embrace every Returning Penitent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, pag.</hi> 87. We muſt above all things put on Charity, and when we come to reprove, rebuke, and to inflict Spiritual Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Puniſhments, we muſt diſtinguiſh as tenderly as we can, between the wilful and the weak, the obſtinate and the Ignorant; the obſtinate we muſt endeavour to ſave with Fear, plucking them out of the Fire, with them we muſt be more ſharp and ſevere in our Admonitions and Threatnings; But on the weak we muſt have Compaſſion, who may be ſuppoſed to Err through ſimplicity, or the fervors of Devotion, and ought to be treated with a fatherly Tenderneſs, for to be reſtored, if poſſible, (conformable unto the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy) with the Spirit of meekneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stop to the Courſe of Separation.</hi> The juſt Reaſons of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation are the ſame all over the World, which is obſtinate perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in great Tranſgreſſions of the general Precepts of the Goſpel. <hi>At the end of the Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151109:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Catholick Church, pag.</hi> 10. Every difference in <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> when no violence is offered to the Catholick Faith and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, muſt not break this Communion, according to that profeſſion of St. <hi>Cyprian, judging no man, nor excluding him from the Right of Communion if he think otherwiſe;</hi> where the diſpute was thought of no mean concernment: Which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> often alledgeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and condemns <hi>Victor, pag.</hi> 11th. who was ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening to Excommunicate the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches for their difference in Celebration of <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>True State of the Primitive Church.</hi> Be charitable to the weak, proceed not ſo ſeverely againſt them in your Courts of Judicature; but Remember what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. in reſpect of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, <hi>Let no man judge you</hi> &amp;c. Will you in reſpect of ſuch ſhadows judge, Excommunicate, Sentence to Everlaſting Flames the Soul that holds of the Body of Chriſt, believes all his Holy Goſpel, accords with you in one Faith, one Baptiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Will you condemn ſuch an one to Eternal Death? God Forbid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformiſts Plea for the Nonconformiſts, Part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 101. We can repreſent and inveigh againſt Schiſm, as the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt. A Sin unto Death indeed in ſome ſence, becauſe it is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Charity and Peace, and deſtructive of the Life of Saints, which doth much conſiſt in their Communion. But were we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial, we ſhould as warmly admoniſh our own hearts to take heed of Schiſmatical Paſſions, and excommunicate them from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, as admoniſh, and caſt out others that differ from us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, pag.</hi> 20. We are forward to blame the more rigid ſort of Separatiſts, for not coming to our Worſhip; and why are we ſo rigid as to forbear all Chriſtian Communion with them, as if Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity were all loſt among them. I do declare, that I hold Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Communion with all the Holy Brethren, and am prepared for Local and External Communion with them in all Chriſtian Duties and Ordinances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond<hi>'s Annotations on the New Teſtament; Rom.</hi> 14.17, 18. Chriſtianity conſiſts not in ſuch External Matters, <hi>[as Meats]</hi> but in the practice of Chriſtian Vertues, ſuch are Mercifulneſs, and Peaceableneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not dividing, and hating, and Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating one another, and 14. <hi>chap. ver.</hi> 13. And therefore let this Fault be mended: do not any longer Cenſure, and ſeperate from one anothers Communion for ſuch things as theſe.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151109:27"/>
            <p>Doctor Hammond <hi>of Schiſm, p.</hi> 16. Becauſe the Governours being men, may poſſibly Err, and conſequently cenſure, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate the innocent, its poſſible the perſon excluded may be innocent: he that is Excommunicate unjuſtly, cannot be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred criminous by that misfortune, <hi>p.</hi> 17. he cites <hi>Photius</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Excommunication of the Jewiſh <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> ſent out againſt Chriſts Diſciples brought them ſo much nearer to their Lord and Maſter, and Alien'd the Jews themſelves, remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them ſo much the farther from the Kingdom of Heaven: and ſo doth all unjuſt Excommunication unite us to the Apoſtles by this Conformity with and participation of their ſufferings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewels <hi>defence of the Apol. p.</hi> 583. <hi>Brings in St. Auguſtine ſaying, Quid obeſt homini,</hi> What is a man the worſe if the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a man ſtrike him out of the <hi>Book of the Church,</hi> if ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſtrike him not out of the Book of Life. In this caſe <hi>St. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith it cometh ſometime to paſs, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t plurimae ſint foris oves, intus Lupi.</hi> That there be many Sheep without the Church, and many Wolves within: And in your own Law (Mr. <hi>Harding</hi>) it is written thus, <hi>Qui illicite alium Excom.</hi> &amp;c. He that unlawfully Excommunicates another condemneth himſelf and not another.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>That our Love must be Catholick.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HOmily of Chriſtian Love and Charity, p.</hi> 36. Charity is to love every man, good and evil, friend and foe; and whatſoever Cauſe be given to the Contrary, yet nevertheleſs to bear good will and heart to every man, to uſe our-ſelves well unto them, as well in Words and countenances, as in all other Acts and deeds; for ſo Chriſt himſelf taught, and ſo alſo he performed indeed, and for as much as the Phariſees with their falſe gloſſes had Corrupted this love of our neighbour, teaching that this love and Charity pertained only unto a mans friends, Chriſt gave this Godly law of Charity a true and clear interpretation, that we ought to love every man, both friend and foe, adding thereto the Commodity to be the Children of our heavenly Father: and this we ſhall be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151109:28"/> ſure of, ſaith Chriſt, if we love every man without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformiſts Plea for Nonconformiſts, Part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 106. The ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Holy Apoſtles expreſſed their largeneſs and their Catholick love to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> among whom were great divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; to the <hi>Galatians</hi> and <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> among whom were ſome very Erroneous: ſo did their Benedictions, peace be to Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jeſus in ſincerity. Eph. 6.23. and verſe 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop Davenants Letter to Duraeus.</hi> Whether we will or no, its neceſſary that we all own Chriſt as our elder Brother, and joyn in ſtrict and Brotherly Communion with all that are his Brethren. Moreover, all muſt confeſſe, true and genuine Charity is as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Salvation of all the Members of the Chriſtan Churches, as the true and entire profeſſion of Saving faith, Chriſt having made this love the Cognizance, Whereby to diſcriminate his diſciples, and thoſe who falſely profeſſe his name, he puts this queſtion, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſafe, Pious, or ſuitable to the duty of Chriſtian Churches, not to ſtretch forth the right hand of Brotherly affection to thoſe Churches, which, though they differ, and in ſome leſſer matters err, may notwithſtanding be Chriſts Martyrs, and our holy Brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Thomas Pierce on St. John the</hi> 13.35. Our love muſt be ſo extenſive, that it muſt reach even to all, not only to our fellow-diſciples, but to all men living upon earth: it muſt reach even to our enemies, not onely to thoſe without the pale of the Church, who do us little or no hurt, even Jews, Turks, Inſidels, and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, for whom we pray once in a year in our Engliſh Liturgy, but to our Crueller enemies within the Church. <hi>P.</hi> 414. <hi>item</hi> 282. Whom our Lord hath enjoyned us not onely to forgive, but pray for, to love their ſouls, to pray for their repentance, and deſire they may be ſharers of immortality and bliſſe: of which we ſhall not have the leſſe, but rather the more, for having ſharers: and <hi>tells us on St. John</hi> 13.35. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my diſciples,</hi> &amp;c Love to Chriſtians as Chriſtians is as the badge and Cognizance, the teſtimony and proof of our real diſcipleſhip under Chriſt, and the firmeſt bond to hold us together in peace and love, not ſo much that we are of one Countrey, but that we are of one Chriſt, or to expreſſe it with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that we have but <hi>One Faith, One Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151109:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> Hammonds <hi>Pract. Catechiſm,</hi> under meekneſs, to continue conſtant to the doctrine of the Catholick Church; and maintain the inward Communion, that of Charity, with all the true Church of God whereſoever they are, and with particular Churches ſo far as to embrace them with the armes of Chriſtian Charity, to joyn even with the erroneous Churches, ſo far as they are not erroneous, Separating onely from their Corruptions, <hi>Idem,</hi> on <hi>firſt Epiſt. of St. John</hi> 3.14. We know that we are regenerate Chriſtians by our Chariry to other men, which he that hath not, is clearly an unregenerate, unchriſtian perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem the firſt Epiſt. St. John</hi> 4.7. And evidence of our being from God, is Charity to our fellow Chriſtians; for that is moſt ſtrictly commanded and exemplified to us from God, and no practice ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders us ſo like to Gods example, and ſo concordant to his precepts, as the ſincere exerciſe of this duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Barrow<hi>'s, Vnity of the Church, annexed to his Treatiſe againſt the Popes Supremacy. P.</hi> 36. The genuine meaning of that article, <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> may reaſonably be deemed this, that we profeſſe our adhering to the body of Chriſtians, which diffuſed over the World, doth retain the ſaith taught, the Diſcipline ſettled, the practiſes appointed by our Lord and Saviour, and his Apoſtles, that we maintain general Charity towards all good Chriſtians, that we are ready to entertain Communion in holy offices with all ſuch. <hi>Item on Rom</hi> 12.18. <hi>pag.</hi> 230, 231. <hi>Serm.</hi> 3. purſue peace with all, without any exception, with men of all Nations, <hi>Jewes,</hi> and <hi>Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Barbarians:</hi> of all Sects, and Religions, perſecute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jews, and Idolatrous Heathens (as at that time;) men of all judgments and perſwaſions; Neither is there any evading our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to this duty, by pretending of others, that they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain opinions irreconcileably contrary to ours, that they adhere to Sects and Parties which we diſlike and diſavow; that they are not ſo vertuous, ſo Religious, ſo Holy, as they ſhould be, or at leaſt not in ſuch a mannner as we would have them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſons <hi>Sermon.</hi> 3. <hi>Ad Aulam ſect.</hi> 39. Here is that evil partiality we are to take heed of when we reſtrain the <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood</hi> (or <hi>Neighbour</hi>) to ſome one party or ſociety (in the Church) ſuch as we think good of, and exclude the reſt, as if they had no part or fellowſhip in this Brotherhood, nor conſequently any right to that ſpecial affection where with we are to <hi>love the Brethren:</hi> which partiailty hath indeed been the very bane of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151109:29"/> Churches unity and peace, and the chief Cauſe both of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and of the Continuance of moſt of the Schiſms, under which Chriſtendom hath groaned from time to time.</p>
            <p>Englands <hi>Black Tribunal, p.</hi> 222. As I am a Member of this Church, ſo I am a Member of the Holy Catholick Church; as I hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with, ſo I love and honour all Chriſtians in the World, that love the ſame Lord Jeſus in ſincerity, and call on his name, agreeing with thoſe Truths, that are abſolutely neceſſary, and clearly demonſtrated in the Word of God, though in charity diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from ſome others, that are not neceſſary, Dr. <hi>Hewyt's Speech at the Scaffold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr <hi>Aleſtrey</hi>'s <hi>Sermon, p.</hi> 168. Our Saviours addition, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44. ſaith, that we muſt <hi>love our Enemies.</hi> The Chriſtians hath no <hi>Canaanites,</hi> as <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. but the moſt proſligate Adverſaries of his Religion he muſt love, and pray for them, although they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him, which makes appear, it doth at leaſt include enemies of Religion; for perſecutions ſeldom were upon any other ground: And Chriſt hath proved that the <hi>Samaritan,</hi> he whom the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples would conſume, that Schiſmatick and rejector of Chriſt, is yet our Neighbour, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. and therefore him alſo we muſt love and pray for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item p.</hi> 322. <hi>Serm.</hi> 18. There is no ſort of men, nor any man, whom it is lawful for a Chriſtian not to love, and all the reaſons urged here by our Saviour do prove, that all mankind, whether good or bad, is the object of a Chriſtians love.</p>
            <p>Mr. Kettlewells <hi>meaſures of Chriſtian Obedience, Edit.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 133, <hi>and</hi> 134. It is not either diſtance of Countrey, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety of intereſt, no, nor what is moſt of all preſumed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt us from the obligations of this duty, diverſity of opinions, or perſwaſions in matters of Religion, which takes away from any man his right to all that kindneſs and advantage from us; but of whatſoever Countrey, Calling or Religion he be, he is our Neighbour meant in <hi>Luke</hi> 10. to whom all the inſtances of love muſt be performed; for what Religion was ever more odious to any one than the <hi>Samaritan</hi> was to the Jews, <hi>John</hi> 8.48. Inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating thereby that any man, though ſo contrary in Religion, as thoſe two were to one another, is the neighbour whom the Law intends.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:151109:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Glanvell<hi>'s Eſſay upon Preaching, pag.</hi> 32. Catholick Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Charity is a Doctrine exceeding ſit for theſe times, in which Diviſions and mutual Animoſities have produced ſo many fatal and deplorable effects; and though the doing this will diſpleaſe the Bygots and Beautefeus of all ſides, yet we muſt go on arm'd with Courage and Patience of the Goſpel, and be inſtant in preaching Peace and Love though we are torn in pieces for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of Real Phyloſophy to Religion, pag.</hi> 32. I ſecure Charity for all the Diverſities of Belief, and equally offer my Friendſhip and Converſes to the ſeveral Sects and Perſwaſions that ſtick to the plain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> principles of the Goſpel and a vertuous life, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlooking their particular Fondneſſes and Follies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Taylor<hi>'s Advice to his Clergy, p.</hi> 29. Let no names of Sects or differing Religion be kept up among you, to the diſturbance of the publick Peace, and private Charity; and teach not the people to eſtimate their Piety by their diſtance from any Opinion, but by their Faith in Chriſt, Obedience, and love to all Chriſtian people, even though they be deceived.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again Rule</hi> 47. Let the buſineſs of your Sermons be to preach Holy Life, Obedience, Peace, Love, among Neighbours Hearty Love, to live as the Old Chriſtians did, and the New ſhould.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Tillotſon<hi>'s Sermon on Luke</hi> 9.55, 56. <hi>pag.</hi> 7. The Goſpel deſigns Univerſal Love and peace and Good Will; and now no difference of Religion, no pretence of Zeal for God and Chriſt can warrant and juſtifie the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem. Vol.</hi> 1. <hi>of Sermons, pag.</hi> 213. When we come to Heaven we ſhall enter into the Society of the Bleſſed Angels, and of the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect; that is freed from all thoſe paſſions and infirmities which do now render the converſation e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the beſt men, ſometimes troubleſome to one another. We ſhall then meet with all thoſe excellent perſons, thoſe innocent and charitable Souls, whom we have ſeen, and heard, and read of in this World, with all intimate Friends, and perhaps with many of our Enemies, to whom we ſhall then be perfectly reconciled, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the warm conteſts, and peeviſh differences which we have had while in this World, even about matters of Religion: For Heaven is a ſtate of perfect Love and Friendſhip; all Quarrels and Contentions, Schiſms and Diviſions will then be effectually hindered, not by Force but by Love, and all thoſe Controverſies
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151109:30"/> of Religion, which are now ſo hotly agitated, will then be finally determined by a perfect knowledge, and convincing Light.</p>
            <p>Lloyd <hi>Biſhop of St.</hi> Aſaph <hi>in Sermon November</hi> 5. 1680. <hi>pag.</hi> 9. We know that Chriſt gave love for the Character by which his Diſciples were to be known, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.35. and leaſt men ſhould unchriſtian others, that they may hate them and deſtroy them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, Chriſt enlarged his precept of love, and extended it even to Enemies, and not onely to ours, but to the Enemies of our Religion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.43, 44.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Cook<hi>'s Sermon on Rom.</hi> 12.18. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. The Church of Chriſt allowes no Enemies at all, but like it, Charity is Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick and Univerſal, nay, like God himſelf Infinite and Eternal, it knows no bounds of Love, nor reſpect of Perſons, and muſt never fail; ſurely then Chriſtianity muſt fail, utterly vaniſh and periſh ſo long as we are at variance among our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, pag.</hi> 10. The grand Duties of Humility, Peace and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Charity, are delivered in the Scriptures, in the moſt plain expreſs and entire manner, as to all Points and Circumſtances of obligation; and therefore whatſoever places are erected againſt thoſe fundamentals of Practice, deſtroy the very eſſence and being of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Catholick Church, pag.</hi> 7. Catholick Unity conſiſts in Unity of Belief, and in the Unity of Charity, having an intimate Fellow-feeling of all the good or evil which befals any, joyned in ſo near a relation as fellow-members, beyond the compaſs of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Humanity, whereby we are bound not onely to pray for, but by all Offices of Kindneſs and moſt intimate Affection, to aſſiſt and relieve each other in the ſame Houſhold of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item. pag.</hi> 53. Many of our Church, yea the conſtitution it ſelf hath been often charged and reviled, though moſt unjuſtly, with too favourable an inclination to them of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe we are not ſo haſty and peremptory in unchurching them altogether, or damning preſently all that have been, or are ſtill of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as ſome would have us; which is in effect for being more tender of preſerving the Principles of true Catholick Unity then in pleaſing ſome private Humours or Prejudices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Pygot<hi>'s Abners Plea for Accom. pag.</hi> 38, 39. Now whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Breaches or Diviſions happen in other Kingdoms, which are without God in the World, and Strangers from the Covenant of Grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.3. yet let <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Church of God be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151109:30"/> like a City which is at Unity within it ſelf: Methinks <hi>Philadelphia</hi> (the name of one of the Seven Golden Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.) is a fitting name for a Church, which ſignifies brotherly Love; and every Congregation ought to be in a good Senſe the <hi>Family of Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item. pag.</hi> 43. Conſider there is but one Body, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4. the whole Church is but one Body, and the Members of the ſame Body do not uſe to contend one with another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Barrow<hi>'s Serm.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 316. I cloſe up all with this Corol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, that if we muſt live lovingly and peaceably with all men, then much more are we obliged to do ſo with all Chriſtians. —Our Spiritual Brethren, Members of the ſame Myſtical Body, Temples of the ſame Holy Ghoſt, Servants of the ſame Lord, Subjects of ſame Prince, Profeſſors of the ſame Truth, partakers of the ſame Hopes, Heirs of the ſame Promiſe, and Candidates of the ſame Everlaſting Happineſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>That an Agreement of all Christians in any one Sect or Perſwaſion is never to be Expected.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIſhop</hi> Jewel<hi>'s Anſwer to Mr.</hi> Harding<hi>'s Preface.</hi> It were above all things to be deſired of God, that his Heavenly Truth may paſs forth without theſe contrarieties and Quarrels of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and many Godly Wiſe Men are much offended to ſee it otherwiſe; but thus it hath been ever from the beginning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir</hi> Francis Bacon <hi>in his Advertiſements of the Controverſies of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 183. <hi>of his works.</hi> It is excellently alluded by that Father, that noted that Chriſts Garment was without Seams, and yet the Churches Garment was of divers colours; and ſets down as a Rule, <hi>In veſte varietas ſit, ſciſſura non ſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt's</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Epistle to the Reader;</hi> That the variety of Mens Minds is ſuch, that <hi>tot Capita tot Senſus;</hi> yea, and that even the very Faces, that God hath by Nature brought forth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151109:31"/> in the World, do every one of them in ſome of their particular Lineaments differ from any other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrew<hi>'s Serm. pag.</hi> 519. Contentions there were, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> and his fellow Apoſtles lived, in the Churches under them of their times, in the very prime of the Primitive Church then were there contentions; this I note, that we may not think it ſtrange if there be contentions in our times, they ſhall be no ſtrangers with us in ours, they were not with them in theirs.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Of the difference in point of Church Government, Sect.</hi> 21. Nor is it any point of Wiſdom or Charity, where Chriſtians dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, (as many do in ſome points) there to widen the differences. <hi>Item,</hi> Upon the many Jealouſies and Scandals rais'd upon the King; 'Tis ſtrange, that ſo Wiſe Men as they would be eſteemed, ſhould not conceive, that difference of perſwaſion in Matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may eaſily fall out, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hooker <hi>of Juſtification, pag.</hi> 68. Ye are not now to learn that as of it ſelf it is not hurtful, ſo neither ſhould it be to any ſcandalous and offenſive, in doubtful caſes to hear the different Judgments of men, be it that <hi>Cephas</hi> hath one interpretation, and <hi>Apollos</hi> another, that <hi>Paul</hi> is of this mind, that <hi>Barnabas</hi> of that: if this offend you the fault is yours. Carry peaceable Minds, and you may have comfort in this variety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Edward Bulkley, <hi>In his Apology for the Church of</hi> England, <hi>Article</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 104. <hi>Edit.</hi> 1608. <hi>in Anſwer to</hi> Wright<hi>'s Articles.</hi> You vainly and falſely exaggerate Controverſies and irreconcila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Jarrs (as you tearm them) among us in eſſential points of Faith. I confeſs, there hath been in our Church ſome Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie concerning External Ceremonies, and Form of Covernment; as there hath been heretofore between good men, as between <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> between <hi>Anicetus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> between <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and many others, who all were godly men, agreeing in unity of Faith, and knowledge of the Son of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hieron<hi>'s Sermons in Bargain of Salt.</hi> Now among our ſelves, betwixt us and other Churches there are ſome differences in Opinion, as it cannot be holpen ſo long as we carry with us our natural imperfections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Chillingworth <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. Becauſe the contrary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief may be in ſuch points, in which Scripture may with great probability be alledged on both ſides; a ſure note of a point not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151109:31"/> neceſſary, that men of honeſt and upright hearts, true lovers of God and of Truth, ſuch as deſire above all things to know Gods will, and to do it, without any fault at all ſome go one way, ſome another, and ſome ſuſpend their judgments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bramhals <hi>Juſt Vindication of the Church,</hi> We ſee that all the famous and principal Churches of the World, the <hi>Grecian, Roman, Proteſtant, Armenian, Abyſſine</hi> have their peculiar differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences one with another, and each of them among themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item p.</hi> 19. Though I am far from beleiving, when <hi>Logomachies</hi> are taken away their real diſſentions are not half ſo numerous, or their errours half ſo foul as they are pointed out by their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet to hold Communion with them in all things is neither lawful nor poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailors <hi>Coll. of diſcourſes in Epiſt. Dedic. before Liberty of Proph.</hi> No part of this diſcourſe teacheth, or encourageth varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sects and contradictions, but ſuppoſeth and finds them alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in being, and therefore ſince there are, and ever were, and ever will be variety of opinions, becauſe there is variety of human underſtandings, and uncertainty in things. Few men conſider, ſince men have ſuch variety of principles ſuch ſeveral conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, educations, tempers, and diſtempers, hopes, intereſts, and weakneſſes, degrees of light, and degrees of underſtanding, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible all ſhould be of one mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item p.</hi> 401. This variety of opinions in ſeveral perſons, an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument only of diverſities of operations while the Spirit is the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhops</hi> Reynolds <hi>Brotherly Reconciler;</hi> In that the Apoſtle ſaith, if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, we may from hence learn that in the beſt ages of the Church there have been, and therefore we cannot but expect that there ever will be, variety and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Judgment among the members thereof; firſt, while we know but in part. Secondly, While there is difficulty in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of Truth. Thirdly, Weakneſs of judgment in men to make that enquiry, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item p.</hi> 19. Till all the members of the Church have attained unto their full Stature, there cannot be expected ſuch an univerſal conſent of Judgments, and harmony of Doctrines, even amongſt good men themſelves as ſhall not admit of ſome variety and diſſonancy.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:151109:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſons <hi>Serm.</hi> 8. <hi>Ad Aulam, Sect.</hi> 25. Mens underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are not all of one ſize and temper, even they that have the largeſt and cleareſt underſtanding, yet know but in part, and are therefore ſubject to errours and miſapprehenſions; therefore it cannot be hoped there ſhould be ſuch a conſonancy and uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Judgment, no not among wiſe and Godly men, but that in many things, yea and things ſometime of great importance, they may and will diſſent one from another unto the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Wilkins <hi>Serm.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 407, 408; 'Tis a thing moſt reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and fitting in it ſelf, [ſpeaking of Moderation] becauſe of the fallibility of human judgment, and that not only from the impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of our faculties, and the prejudices we are liable to from the account of intereſts, but likely from the difficulty and obſcurity of things, the moſt Learned and inquiſitive men many times dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in their judgments, all which put together ſhew how exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing difficult, and next to impoſſible it is that men ſhould ever agree in the ſame apprehenſions of things.</p>
            <p>Glanvell's <hi>Catholick Charity, p.</hi> 34. The Learned and the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Churches, and Councels, Confeſſors, and Fathers, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and the latter ages, the vertuous, and the devout, the credulous and the inquiſitive, they have all differed in the leſſer matters of belief, and every man differs from almoſt every other in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>p.</hi> 37. 'Tis a frequent wiſh with ſome that all men were once of one mind, but then it muſt be theirs no doubt, for they would not judge it reaſonable upon other terms. They may as well wiſh that we were all of one age, complexion, humour, and degree of underſtanding. 'Tis enough that ſuch agreement is not neceſſary, yea I take the other ſtep, 'tis impoſſible. Our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Capacities, Educations, Genius's, Converſes, Intereſts, Accidents are ſtrangely divers, therefore our apprehenſions muſt needs be different.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Decay of Piety, p.</hi> 409; Not that I ſuppoſe it poſſible to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh all diverſities of opinions among men, who from their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering faculties, and other guiltleſs occurrents may and will have their judgments ſeverally diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Barrows <hi>Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>Serm.</hi> 8. Men ſeeing by ſeveral lights, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing by diverſly diſpoſed palates, and meaſuring things by differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtandards, we can hardly do or ſay any thing Religious or Civil, which if approved or applauded by ſome, will not be diſliked and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151109:32"/> blamed by others in this irreconcileable diverſities and inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of mens apprehenſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſign of Chriſtianity,</hi> Chriſtians becauſe of the diverſities of their capacities, educations, and other means and advantages, ſome points may be moſt plainly perceived by ſome to be delivered in the Scripture, which cannot be ſo by others with the like eaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Stillingfleets <hi>Irenicum, p.</hi> 21. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2. The peace and ſettlement of Chriſts Church not depending upon a condition never likely to be attained in this world, which is the agreement and uniformity of mens opinions; for as long as mens faces differ their judgments will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The True ſtate of the primitive Church, p.</hi> 2. Mens underſtandings are as various as their ſpeech or their countenance; otherwiſe it were impoſſible there ſhould be ſo many underſtanding and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, yea and conſcientious men alſo Papiſts, Lutherans, Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, all in ſuch oppoſition one againſt another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conf. Plea for the Non-Conformiſts, part.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 40. How vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are the degrees of light, and the dictates of Conſcience even in good, wiſe, and ſelf-ſearching men, and that even in a diviſion of judgment and practice! The firſt cauſe is different degrees of Light, and means of attaining knowledge: Some are more deep and quick, ſearching and induſtrious, have better means and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of knowing: I do not now take notice of the biaſſes of education, prejudice, pre-poſſeſſions, and paſſions of Men, nor the influence of the world upon mens alterations.</p>
            <p>Kidders <hi>Sermon of peace, p.</hi> 24. It is indeed very poſſible after all that the beſt men may differ from each other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Wakes <hi>Sermon</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.5, 6, 7. <hi>p.</hi> 8. Mens different ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, and opportunities, and tempers, and educations conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, 'tis in vain to expect that all good men ſhould agree in all their notions of Religion, any more then we ſee they do in any other concerns whatſoever. And <hi>p.</hi> 9. That mens underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are different, and they will argue different ways, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain different opinions from one another about the ſame things, and yet may nevertheleſs deſerve on all ſides to be eſteemed very good and wiſe men for all that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry,</hi> It is true indeed there may be, and muſt be diverſities of apprehenſions in ſeveral points of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, while men are of different capacities.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:151109:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Cooks <hi>Sermon,</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 12, 18, p. 7. It cannot poſſibly be meant their agreement in judgment, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12, 16. for that you know cannot be forced, one mans mind (though he would him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) cannot always be bent to anothers perſwaſion: yet there are ſome among us, great pretenders too to holineſs, who value no agreement like that in principles; if they can but meet with a man that jumps with them in ſentiments, he is cheriſhed and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced as a knowing man, well enclined and diſpoſed to good things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument for Tol. in differences of Opinion, Printed</hi> 81. <hi>p.</hi> 2. Had God intended we ſhould be all of one opinion, as indeed that we ſhould be of one Faith, he could have made every thing as clear and plain in the Holy Scripture, and as undoubted as any <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>Idem.</hi> By way of illuſtration let us make a ſuppoſal, that a Maſter bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth three or four of his Servants do ſuch or ſuch a thing, and that the Servants differ about the ſenſe and meaning of the command, one underſtanding it one way, another another way, and a third in this, the fourth in that, according to the judgment of their own diſcretion; and this is our Caſe we all are equally ſervants not bound to that ſenſe of the word which another gives, indeed ſome ſervants are to bring the word to others, but thoſe others not bound to the ſenſe of it further than they are perſwaded it is their Maſters: ſearch the Scriptures, and try the ſpirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Principles and Practices of Moderation. &amp;c. p.</hi> 310. It is no leſs unreaſonable to malign our brethren becauſe they are not in every thing of our judgment, than to quarrel with each other upon the account of the unlikeneſs we obſerve in our faces and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Tulli's <hi>Sermon of Moderation, p.</hi> 17. Let us not therefore, if we have any ſenſe of Moderation and temper, perſiſt to dreſs up things in hideous and portentous ſhapes to frighten and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate one another, but let us rather aſcribe the differences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us to error of judgment, the prejudices of education, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicity of Conſtitution, or to any other of thoſe either innocent or excuſable cauſes, which render an intire unity of opinions an impoſſible thing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151109:33"/>
            <head>That Mutual Favour and Forbearance of one another in Love is neceſſary among Christians in their Diverſities of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
            <p>EDward <hi>the Sixth, Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt, King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt and Second, and King</hi> James <hi>the Second,</hi> all gave their Toleration and Indulgence to the ſeveral Churches Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from us; the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Colcheſter, Walloones</hi> at <hi>Norwich,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> and at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or elſewhere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt of Bleſſed Memory, in his Letters to the States of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, March</hi> 6. 1613. Magis Autem e re fore, ſi Miniſtris veſtris ſtricte imperetis, ut pacem colant ſe invicem to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerando in iſta opiniorum &amp; ſententiarum diſcrepantia. —Eoque juſtius videmur vobis hoc ipſum ſuadere debere, quod neutram comperimus adeo deviam, ut non poſſint &amp; cum fidei Chriſtianae veritate, &amp; cum animarum ſalute conſiſtere. But it would be more advantageous, if you did give a ſtrict charge to your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to keep the Peace by mutual Toleration of one another in the difference of Opinions and Judgments. And therefore we ſeem more juſtly to give you this Counſel, becauſe we find neither of theſe Opinions ſo Erroneous, but that they may conſiſt with the Truth of the Chriſtian Faith, and the Salvation of their Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall<hi>'s Letters to</hi> Duraeus. Why do we profeſs Chriſtian Charity if we do pertinaciouſly refuſe to Indulge the difference of our Brethren from us in theſe Scholaſtick Problems (ſo he calls the differences between <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi>) when we know that our benign Saviour moſt mildly tolerated, and ſilently paſſed by more grievous in his own Domeſticks.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151109:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt's Meſſage of a Treaty from</hi> Oxford, <hi>March</hi> 3. 1643. He deſired the Members of both Houſes of Parliament to conſult and agree upon ſuch things, as might conduce to the maintenance and defence of the Reformed Proteſtant Religion, with due conſideration for all juſt and reaſonable eaſe to tender Conſciences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item in the Kings Second Meſſage for Peace, January</hi> 29, 1645. That by the Liberty offered in the fifteenth preſent for the eaſe of their Conſciences, who communicate not in the Service already eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament in this Kingdom, he intends, that all other Proteſtants behaving themſelves peaceably in and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Civil Government ſhall have the free exerciſe of their Religion in their own way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item to the Prince of Wales.</hi> The charitable connivance, and Chriſtian Toleration often diſſipates their ſtrength whom rougher oppoſition fortifies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond<hi>'s Sermons pag.</hi> 72. I am confident there were no ſuch way of deſigning a proſperous flouriſhing durable King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as to found its Polity upon Goſpel Principles, and maintain it by the Goſpel Spirit (<hi>id eſt,</hi> of Love and Meekneſs) I have Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to think that was the meaning of the Propheſie of Chriſts turning Swords into Plough-ſhares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Advice to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>Roman Catholicks, and Proteſtant Diſſenters tells us, pag.</hi> 23. Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> left it to the Witneſſes of his End as his dying Counſel to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they diſplaced no man out of the Univerſities, or preſent Church; but that by Love, and an Holy Life they ſhould prevail upon thoſe in poſſeſſion then, to come into their Church. Which he had (as he tells us) from an eminent hand in <hi>Oxford,</hi> a year or two af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Doctors Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hales <hi>of Erring Chriſtians, pag.</hi> 26. <hi>Edit.</hi> 2. The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were called <hi>Chreſtiani</hi> from a word ſignifying benignity and ſweetneſs. What reaſon is there why that ſhould not be one of the chiefeſt notes of the Church of Chriſt, which did ſo eſpecially characterize a Chriſtian man, except there were a decay of it at this day in the Church? <hi>Georgius</hi> a Factious Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> is ſaid <hi>oblitus profeſſionis ſuae, quae nil niſi juſtum ſuadet &amp; bene;</hi> Quite beſides his profeſſion, whoſe eſpecial notes were Gentleneſs and Equity, in the ſenſe of the Heathen <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second in a Declaration from</hi> Breda, was for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151109:34"/> Liberty to Tender Conſciences, and ſayes that no man ſhall be diſquieted for Differences in Opinion in Matters of Religion, which do not diſturb the Peace of the Kingdom, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. and 18. This Declaration his Majeſty afterwards, <hi>May</hi> 8. 1661. tearms a Promiſe ſolemnly made. This Declaration or Promiſe he tells both Houſes, <hi>July</hi> 8, 1661. that ſo oft as he comes to them he menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons his Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> that himſelf as well as they might mind it. In his <hi>Majeſties Declaration of Decemb.</hi> 26, 1662. He tells us, that he remembers the very words of the Promiſes from <hi>Breda</hi> that concern'd Liberty of Conſcience, and the confirmations he hath made of them ſince upon ſeveral Occaſions, and that he is ſtill firm in Reſolution of performing them to the full. He tells what hindered; But it muſt not be wondered at, ſince that Parliament to which thoſe promiſes were made in relation to an Act, never thought fit to offer us any to that purpoſe. His Majeſty publickly declared his avowed readineſs in his Proclamation, <hi>July</hi> 16. 1669. to indulge Tender Conſciences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bramhall<hi>'s Juſt Vindication, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 279. Men may vary in their Judgments, and yet preſerve Chriſtian Unity and Charity in their Affections one towards another, ſo as Errours be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Fundamental Articles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Gauden <hi>of ſlight Healing, pag.</hi> 102. That Lenitive of Equanimity, Forbearance, and Moderation (in reſpect of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Diſſenters from the publick Conſent, Cuſtoms and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions in the Church) which Chriſtian Charity requires, and publick peace with ſafety may bear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, pag.</hi> 93. Scandalous for any to plead that they may have Liberty or Toleration for that, which by publique Advice, and upon due ſearch is found to be ſuch, as is prone to endanger, or diſorder and infect the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Reynold<hi>'s Brotherly Reconciliation, pag.</hi> 19. In this caſe of unavoidable differences among good men, there ought to be Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Charity, Meekneſs, Moderation, Tolerance, Humanity uſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, pag.</hi> 25. Brings in a ſaying of Mr. <hi>Calvin;</hi> ſuch a man (ſaith he) is a ſincere Miniſter of Chriſt, a godly and a moderate Man, therefore, though he diſſent from us, I will not ceaſe to love him ſtill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Taylor<hi>'s Collection of Diſcourſes, pag.</hi> 603. To refuſe our Charity to thoſe who have the ſame Faith, becauſe they have not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151109:35"/> all our Opinions, and believe not every thing neceſſary which we over-value, is Impious and Schiſmatical; and to this ſenſe is that of St. <hi>Paul, If I had all Faith, and have not Charity, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem.</hi> If men pleaſe, what-ever advantages would be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to an Unity of perſwaſion may be ſupplied by a charitable compliance, and mutual permiſſion of Opinion, preſcribed us by the Lawes of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, Epiſt. before Lib. of Proph. in Collection of Diſcourſes,</hi> &amp;c. I thought it might not misbecome my duty and endeavours, to plead for Peace and Charity, and Forgiveneſs, and Permiſſions mutual. And in <hi>Defence of that Piece in the Second Edition.</hi> Now I have done all that I can do; onely I cannot repent me of ſpeaking Truth, or doing Charity. I Anſwer, whatſoever is againſt the Foundation of Faith, or contrary to good Life, and the Lawes of Obedience, or deſtructive to humane Societies, and the publick and juſt intereſts of Bodies Politick; is out of the limits of my Queſtion for Toleration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem,</hi> I think I have ſpoken reaſon in my Book, and examined it with all the ſeverity that I have, I writ this, becauſe I thought it was neceſſary, and ſeaſonable, and charitable, and agreeable to the great precepts and deſign of Chriſtianity, conſonant to the practice of the Apoſtles, and of the beſt Ages of the Church, and of the nature of the thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hacket's <hi>Sermon on Acts</hi> 5.39. <hi>p.</hi> 22. An Unanimity of Opinions is not neceſſary to Friendſhips, ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> very well. Dear Friends may retain the ſweetneſs of love together, and yet vary in ſome concluſion of Judgments; a little more may be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that each may be earneſt to win the other to aſſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, pag.</hi> 25. But if ſundry ſhapes and appearances of reaſon will not ſuffer us all to enjoy the ſame Knowledge, and the ſame Conſcience, yet let us Diſſent as Brethren, and not as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon<hi>'s Serm.</hi> 9. <hi>ad Aulam, Sect.</hi> 23. We ſee Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, Lawyers, and Phyſitians, confuting one anothers Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in great Volumes, and we allow it in them; but difference in Opinions is more tolerable in Divinity, by how much the things about which we are converſant are of a more ſublime, myſterious, and of an incomprehenſible Nature, than are thoſe of other Sciences.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151109:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Wilkins <hi>Sermons on Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>p.</hi> 57. There are ſeveral Truths which are not of ſo great conſequence as Unity, Peace and Charity; and therefore in ſuch things there ought to be a mutual forbearance towards one another. <hi>Idem Sermon</hi> 13. It is no difficult matter for men to be fair and kind, and moderate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch as are of the ſame way and agree with them in the main. <hi>Idem pag</hi> 413. 414. This vertue Moderation will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry advantageous to the peace and welfare of human ſociety in the general, which doth very much depend upon the mutual conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion and forbearance of men towards one another with things about which they differ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Preface to Dr.</hi> Worthingtons <hi>Scripture-Catechiſm,</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Author deceaſed; among other there were no vertues he was obſerved to be more an example of then a Dove-like innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſimplicity, Meekneſs, Humility, and peaceableneſs, candor and ingenuity the moſt Chriſtian, becauſe the greateſt and moſt univerſal Charity, in which thoſe that diſſented in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, (which is rare in theſe days) had not onely a real but a great intereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Aleſtries <hi>Sermons;</hi> If you would diſcover what the temper of the Goſpel is, you may ſee it in its Prophecy and Picture in the Prophet, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 11.6, 7.65, 25. The Wolf ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard ſhall lye down with the Kid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever miſchief theſe have in themſelves there is nothing of devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or of hurt to one another in this ſtate, they lye down and dwell together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again Sermon</hi> 18. <hi>p</hi> 36. In the name of God what did Chriſt mean when he preſcribed this Precept, when he diſputed, preſt it thus upon us, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.44. Or what do Chriſtians mean when they do break and tear this precept and themſelves. Though I be far from any hopes to reconcile our parties, (as by Gods help I ſhall ever be from making any) yet I will offer an expedient to make them not ſo noxious, namely if they will keep the difference of their judgments from breaking out into their affections and actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Barrow <hi>Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>Sermon</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 250, 251. It concerns us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we would live peaceably in ſuch diſputable matters, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all due reverence to the judgments of the moſt, the beſt, and wiſeſt perſons, to be contented in a modeſt privacy to enjoy the reſults of a ſerious and impartial diſquiſition, patiently enduring
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151109:36"/> others to diſſent from us; and not attempting by needleſs fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and endleſs contentions to gain others to our perſwaſions, eſpecially ſince the Truth contended for may not be worth the paſſion employed about it. <hi>Idem Serm.</hi> 8th. againſt Evil ſpeaking <hi>p.</hi> 67. 'Tis very unjuſt when as we do need the candid judgment, and forbearance, and pardon of others for many things faulty and offenſive that we commit, to refuſe the like to others.</p>
            <p>Glanvells <hi>Catholick Charity, p.</hi> 29. Seeing then that Charity is neceſſary, and agreement in opinions is neither neceſſary, nor poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible we ought to comply with our main duty notwithſtanding our leſſer difference. If this were conſidered unity of affection might be preſerved amidſt diverſity of opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And p.</hi> 20. Then will the Church be glorious indeed when Chriſtians ſhall make differences in opinions, and diſpenſable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, the objects of their mutual forbearance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem p.</hi> 59. If any ſhould now ask me whether this Doctrine of Univerſal Love does not tend to univerſal Toleration, I ſhould anſwer that thus far it doth, that all private perſons ſhould To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate each other, and bear with their brothers infirmities, that every man ſhould allow another that Liberty, which he deſires himſelf in what the Laws of God and Man have left him free, and permit him his own opinion without cenſure or diſpleaſure: But as to the publick, I do by no means think it modeſt for us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what the Government ſhould do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Mores <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity, and Anſwer touching Liberty in Religion, p.</hi> 542. I ſay then for all Proteſtants Churches whoſe Religion is the Bible, it is little detriment or indecorum for them to uſe ſo well a limited indulgence (as I have above deſcribed) to their weak but ſincere nurſlings, who are ſo thorough formed Chriſtians, as cordially to believe all the eſſential parts of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but are onely puzled in ſome opinions and ſcrupuloſities that are preter-eſſentials. It is no more unſeemly to permit ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to them peculiarly, than for a tender Mother to indulge ſomething to a Child that breeds teeth, or is any otherways weak or ſickly; or a Maſter of a Family to permit, if not provide ſome proper accommodations for thoſe of his Family a part, whoſe infirmities or conſtitutions make them leſs fit to dine or ſup at his common Table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem Miſtery of Godlineſs, Preface p.</hi> 19. A mutual Agreement in bearing with one another diſſents in the non fundamentals of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151109:36"/> Religion is really a greater ornament of Chriſtianity than the moſt exact Uniformity imaginable, it being an eminent exerciſe of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the flower of all Chriſtian Graces, and the beſt way (I think) at a long run to make the Church as uniform, as can juſtly be deſired.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Author of the Whole Duty of Man.</hi> The leſſer differences in opinion, muſt be born with on both ſides and muſt not in the leaſt abate our brotherly Charity to each other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop of St.</hi> Aſaph's <hi>Sermon on</hi> 5th. <hi>November before the Houſe of of Lords.</hi> As our Holy Religion excells all other in this admirable temper of love, ſo by this we may uſually judge who they are that excell among Chriſtian Churches, when there happens any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury's <hi>Hiſtory of the Rights of Princes, pag.</hi> 257, 258. It is obſervable, the beſt of Clergy-men have been the moſt gentle to thoſe that differed from them. But the unworthy who will not trouble themſelves with the laborious methods of conquering errors, are always apt to extream and cruel courſes, ſince they know they muſt prevail with theſe, or none at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Caves <hi>Goſpel Preached to the Romans, pag.</hi> 84; The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts which our Lord gives, and moſt earneſtly recommends in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the general benefit of mankind, are thoſe of Meekneſs, Mercy, Forbearance, Long-ſuffering, brotherly Kindneſs, and Charity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Stillingfleets <hi>Irenicum Preface;</hi> There were after this Decree at <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 15.29. great diverſities of practice, and diverſities of Obſervations among Chriſtians, but the Holy Ghoſt never thought them fit to be made matters of Law, to which all parties ſhould conform; all that the Apoſtles required as to theſe was mutual forbearance, and condeſcentions towards each other in them. <hi>And in Pref. to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation he pleads for favour for them and forbearance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> De l' Angle, In the Name of God my Lord (in his Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi>) do all that poſſibly you can to bring them back to their duty by ſweetneſs and Charity which is onely able to do great things on theſe occaſions; for men who have always ſomething of pride, do commonly oppoſe every thing thot ſeems to them to act by bare Authority only, they ſcarce ever fail to yield themſelves up to forbearance and condeſcention. I ſhall alſo here mention the judgment of divers eminent Paſtors
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151109:37"/> of the French Church in thoſe Irenical diſcourſes, Geſel <hi>Hiſt. part</hi> 2. It were in the firſt place to be wiſhed that all who do profeſs the Diſcipline of Chriſt would think and ſpeak the ſame thing: but ſince the weakneſs of humane underſtandings, this difficulty of Divine things is ſo great, that ſuch an abſolute conſent amongſt pious perſons is ſcarcely to be expected in this World, the next thing to be endeavoured after is that they may agree in the belief of the principle Heads of our Religion; and as for other things which neither of neceſſity belong to Holineſs of Life, nor the comfort of Souls, nor the Kingdom of God, that men would ſo believe them, as to bear with them who think otherwiſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. For that this may lawfully be done the thing it ſelf declares, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> pronounceth; not onely in many places doth permit, but even commands us to bear with Diſſenters: This is the common opinion of all perſons, which from the firſt ages of Chriſtianity to the preſent times have been of any eſteem or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Principles and Practices of ſome Moderate Divines, p.</hi> 308. Let the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity labour for the true ſpirit and temper of Chriſtians, and it will be as well with the Chriſtian World as if we were all of the ſame mind; I mean let us not Magiſterially im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon one another, and be ſo Charitable as to believe well of Diſſenters from us that live good lives. <hi>Item p.</hi> 348. That we may contend with each other about nothing more then who ſhall expreſs in the midſt of our different perſwaſions moſt Charity and moſt Candor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformiſt Plea to the Non-Conformiſt, part</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 62. Doth Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Love and Compaſſion prompt us, to wiſh our perſecuted Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>France</hi> enjoyed the liberty of the true Religion there? And if they ſhould enjoy a freedom there, ſhall we deny a liberty to Proteſtant Brethren here? I can ſee no ways to avoid a Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the barbarous uſage of Proteſtants there, by them that proſecute Proteſtants here?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem part</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 1. Peace, Love, and Forbearance have a greater place aſſigned them in Religion, than the things in controverſie, which cauſe our Diviſions. And whether it be Meeter for the greater things to ſuffer by the leſſer, or the leſſer to give place to the greater, let common reaſon judge, and common experience come in as an evidence.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:151109:37"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Kidder<hi>'s Serm. of Peace, pag.</hi> 24. The beſt men as they may differ from each other, but then their Chriſtian charity will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to forbear, and forgive, and to debate with great calmneſs and temper; which is the way at once to Truth and Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Tully<hi>'s Serm. of Moderation, pag.</hi> 2. Thoſe Homiletic, or if I may ſo ſpeak, converſable Graces of Meekneſs, Gentleneſs, Forgiveneſs, Forbearance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſo frequently preſſed upon us in the Sacred Writings, upon this proſpect partly, no doubt, that they all of them tend mightily to the ſweetning of Societies, and to the prevention, or healing thoſe differences which are apt to embroil us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument for Toleration and Indulgence in relation to differences in Opinion, pag.</hi> 2. We muſt diſtinguiſh between points of Faith and Points of Opinion; that we ought to bear one with another in reſpect of differing Opinions as God doth bear with us all: he hath left ſomethings leſs plain and clear then others as matters both to exerciſe the reaſonable faculties of good and pious men, and to afford them ſubjects of mutual Charity and Forbearance in their different Sentiments and Apprehenſions about them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, pag.</hi> 25. As for Separations into ſeveral and diſtinct Conventions, I ſee no cauſe of fearing any greater inconvenience in them to the Church, or to the State, if mutual Toleration and Indulgence be the received Principle, than is in ſo many ſeveral Clubs of Friendſhip, or Companies of Trade. However different they may be from one another, in other reſpects, in this they will all agree to love one another for that of God they ſee, and to maintain the publick Liberty, the common Intereſt of all, and ſo though they are as many Conventions as you can imagine, (and the more the leſs dangerous, one will balance another) yet they are not Factions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Form of Prayer, Dec.</hi> 22. 1680. By the power of thy Holy Spirit of Peace, diſpoſe all our Hearts to ſuch Meekneſs of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſuch calm and deliberate Long-Suffering and Forbearance of one another in Love, that ſo we may live in Peace, and the God of Peace may be with us.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151109:38"/>
            <head>That Force and Capital Puniſhments are not to be Inflicted on Chriſtians for their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Opinions from us.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOod Advice to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 22. And to the end that I may do the Reformation Right, and the Principles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Juſtice, thoſe in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Time, particularly <hi>Latimer, Philpot, Bradford, Rogers,</hi> very eminent Reformers, hardly one perſon of any Note but did paſs Sentence on Perſecution as Anti-chriſtian; the Apologies after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the ſame ſtrain as may be ſeen in <hi>Juel, Haddon, Reynolds,</hi> &amp;c. cenſuring the Papiſts for the Perſecutions that they raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proteſtants for matters of pure Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Juel<hi>'s Defence of the Apol. pag.</hi> 484. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nullis bonis in Catholica Eccleſia hoc placet ſi uſque ad mortem in quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam licet haereticum ſaeviatur.</hi> No good man in the Catholick Church likes that any Heretick ſhould be puniſhed with Death. As for our parts, ſpeaking of our Church, we were never yet guilty to one drop of your blood. We ſeek no Aid at Fire and Sword, we will rather ſay with St. <hi>Jerom; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam filios haereticorum,</hi> &amp;c. Would God we may kill the Children of Hereticks, and of all them that be deceived with Spiritual Arrows, that is to ſay with the Teſtimonies of Scripture. And with St. <hi>Auguſtine, O ſi occidas eos gladio bis acuto,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrew's <hi>Sermons on Luk.</hi> 9.54, 55, 56. <hi>pag.</hi> 912. He puts the caſe; whether the Town of <hi>Samaria</hi> for not receiving Chriſt upon pretence he was not of their Religion might not be conſumed; but Chriſt ruleth the Caſe for the Town, that it ought not to be done. It was an Errour, this of the two Diſciples, we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151109:38"/> ſee it plain by <hi>Neſcitis;</hi> but of it may well be ſaid that <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith of another of theirs, <hi>O ſalutaris error, &amp;c.</hi> Bleſſed Errour it was, for by it the World was rid of the like Errour ever after. For ſo long as this verſe ſhall ſtand in this Goſpel it will ſerve for a reſolution to this Queſtion. Any of his Diſciples may do that which they here would have done. This rebuke here of theſe will reach to all undertakers in the ſame kind; this <hi>Non perdere ſed ſalvare</hi> ſaves all our Towns, Cities and States from conſuming by fire, from any of Chriſts Company.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item pag.</hi> 919. And where they move him <hi>in ſpecie</hi> for a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by Fire, he not content to deny that alone, denieth it <hi>in genere,</hi> not to deſtroy at all, neither by Fire, nor any other way. Here we have a caſe of Fire; will ye have another of the Sword?</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> 22.49. Shall we ſmite with the Sword? that he denies too: Out with your Fire <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> up with your Sword <hi>Peter.</hi> So that neither by fire here, nor by Sword there, doth Chriſt like of theſe Motions. If ſo oft as Chriſt ſuffers indignity, fire ſhould come down from Heaven, <hi>Domine quis ſuſtinebit? Pſal.</hi> 130.3. We were all in an hard caſe, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans,</hi> yea Diſciples, yea this <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> and all. The <hi>Samaritans</hi> they received not Chriſt, let them be gone, burnt all. When he came to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> why, there he was murthered, worſe uſed then in <hi>Samaria;</hi> then we muſt call for more fire, <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> muſt be burnt too. Now for the Diſciples, it is true, they had received him; but when moſt need was, thruſt him from them, utterly denied, that ever they knew him: then we muſt trouble Heaven once more, and call for fire for <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> too: nay, then the World is at an end, <hi>facti ſumus ſicut Sodoma, Rom.</hi> 9.12. all an heap of aſhes, if this Doctrine go forward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, pag.</hi> 913. And for our comfort 'tis, that our Saviour Chriſt was none of theſe <hi>Zelotae,</hi> but ſhewed himſelf on that ſide that enclined to Humanity and Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt's Speech to the Lords and Commons at</hi> White-Hall, <hi>March</hi> 21, 1609. I never found that Blood, and too much ſeverity did good in Matters of Religion; For beſides that it is a ſure Rule in Divinity, and God never loves to plant his Church by Violence and Bloodſhed, Natural Reaſon may even perſwade us, and all Experience proves it true.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his Majeſties retirement from</hi> Weſtminſter. Sure
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151109:39"/> it ceaſeth to be Counſel, when not Reaſon is uſed as to men, but Force and Terrour as to Beaſts; to drive men, and compel them to aſſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the calling in of the</hi> Scots <hi>and their coming. Sect.</hi> 11. Sure in Matters of Religion thoſe Truths gain moſt on mens Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Conſciences, which are leaſt urged with ſecular Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which weakens Truth with Prejudices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Covenant, Ejac.</hi> 2. Nothing violent or injurious can be Religious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, On the Rebellions and Troubles in Ireland, Sect.</hi> 12. O my God, thou ſeeſt how much Cruelty among Chriſtians is acted under the colour of Religion, as if we could not be Chriſtians, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we Crucifie one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Chillingsworth, <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. Take away this perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting, burning, curſing, damning of men for not ſubſcribing to the words of men, as the words of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In a word, take away Tyranny, which is the Devils inſtrument to ſupport Errours, and Superſtitions, and Impieties in the ſeveral parts of the World, which could not otherwiſe long with-ſtand the Power of Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir</hi> Robert Pointz <hi>Vindication of Monarchy, pag.</hi> 27. The Sword availeth little with the Souls of Men, unleſs to deſtroy them with their Bodies, and to make them deſperate, or diſſemblers in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and when they find opportunity, to fall into Rebellion; as there are many Examples.</p>
            <p>Pygot<hi>'s Abners Plea.</hi> Shall we prove <hi>homo homini lupus,</hi> one man a Wolf to another, to hunt and to worry and to kill one another? It is againſt nature. It's for bruit beaſts that have no underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bite and tear, and gore one another; but as for men, they ſhould be Meek and Gentle, <hi>homo homini Deus,</hi> one man ſhould be Godlike to another, to help, and to defend, and to comfort one another. <hi>Page</hi> 46. Conſider that ſuch things will bring a ſcandal upon our Religion. The Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were noted to be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Kings. And the Proteſtant Religion hath hitherto been noted to be a merciful, a peaceable Religion. —They are our Spiritual Brethren, our Chriſtian Brethren; and though nature cannot, yet Grace ſhould prevail with us, to return from following our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Brethren, thoſe that profeſs the ſame Faith, and the ſame Proteſtant Religion with us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second, December</hi> 26, 1662. 'Tis evident <hi>(ſaid his Majeſty)</hi> by the ſad Experience of Twelve Years, there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151109:39"/> is very little fruit of all thoſe forcible Courſes, that have been uſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feb.</hi> 5. 1672. <hi>The then Lord Chancellor in his Speech of his Majeſty</hi> Charles the 2d. He loves not blood, nor rigorous ſeverities; but where mild or gentle ways may be uſed by a wiſe Prince, he is certain to chooſe them,— And concludes that head thus; But His Majeſty is not convinced that violent ways are the intereſt of Religion or the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Gauden <hi>of ſlight Healing, p.</hi> 46. While men of the ſame Polity are like Pikes in a Pond, or Fiſh in the Sea, or beaſts of prey in a Wilderneſs, purſuing and devouring one another. While they have ſo little Equity, ſo no Piety or Charity to each other; but every party deſigns to ſubdue others, to ſet up it ſelf, and to oppreſs the common liberty, and publick welfare, what peace in Church or State. <hi>Item p.</hi> 25. When true Religion is either cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in its ſoundneſs of Doctrine, or overgrown by Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, broken by Faction, or perſecuted by miſguided Zeal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor<hi>'s Advice to his Clergy, p.</hi> 25. Uſe no violence to any man to bring him to your opinion, but by the word of your Miniſtery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> —Conſtrain them to come in. <hi>Rule</hi> 28. Stir up no violence againſt them, but leave them if they be incurable, to the wiſe and merciful diſpoſition of the Law. <hi>Idem,</hi> if a man cannot change his opinion when he liſt, nor ever doth heartily, but when he cannot do otherwiſe, (<hi>i. e.</hi> through his own convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) then to uſe force may make him an Hypocrite, but never aright believer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon <hi>ad Aulam Serm.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 34. A ſad thing it is, and very grievous it is to the Soul of every good man, when in the Church, which is the houſe of God, Chriſtians that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves brethren, fall foul upon one another, not onely girding at, and claſhing againſt, but biting and nipping, and devouring one another, as if they were bent to conſume and to deſtroy one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hackets <hi>Serm. on Acts</hi> 15.39. <hi>p.</hi> 38. I have caſt my mite at this time into the Treaſury, to remind them who are of the ſame lot before Chriſt with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> to ſtop contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and as they dread the ſharp wrath of God to mitigate all ſharpneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Barrows <hi>Treatiſe of the Popes Supremacy, p.</hi> 219: Men not to preſcribe to others or not to Perſecute for them. And <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151109:40"/> of the Church annexed to it, p.</hi> 11. Who-ever therefore doth high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offend againſt Charity, maligning or miſchieving his brethren, doth thereby ſeparate himſelf from Chriſts body, and ceaſe to be a Chriſtian, and cites St. <hi>Auguſtine de Bapt.</hi> 3.19. They that are enemies to brotherly Charity they are Pſeudo-Chriſtians, and Anti-Chriſt, they are ſeparate from the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Alleſtries <hi>Sermons, p.</hi> 165. To deſtroy mens lives, or other temporal rights, on this account meerly becauſe they are Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, Schiſmaticks, or otherwiſe reject the true Religion, or Chriſt himſelf, this is that which Chriſt reproves here, telling them that would do ſo, <hi>you know not what manner of Spirit you are of. Item Serm.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 170. If mens falſe opinions make no parties, nor miſchief in the State, we are not to make them Martyrs to their falſe opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cauſes of Decay of Piety, p.</hi> 184. They know little of Ancient, and leſs of modern times, that are not acquainted with the mutual perſecutions, which almoſt all parties have alternately raiſed one againſt another among Chriſtians; Confiſcations and Baniſhments, Gibbets and Flames, Weapons, God knows, much too carnal for a ſpiritual Warfare; yet much more in uſe, then thoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> recommends to <hi>Timothy, Gentleneſs and Meek inſtructing of oppoſers,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25, 26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Stewards <hi>Sermons on</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.22. <hi>p.</hi> 15. A caſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience decided by our Saviours own mouth in St. <hi>Luke</hi> 9. <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the two <hi>ſons of Thunder</hi> begins ſtraightway to ſhew their temper. What! not receive Chriſt, nor the Chriſtian Faith! Maſter, ſhall we command fire from heaven? Our Saviour replies, you <hi>know not what manner of Spirit you are of,</hi> ye underſtand not at all what it is to be a Chriſtian, I came not to deſtroy, to plant Religion in blood, no, I leave that to Turks and to Mahometans <hi>p.</hi> 16. Its not lawful by blood to bring in Chriſtian Faith: Its not lawful to plant a Church by ſuch force, nor is it lawful thus to reform it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Henry Mores <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity, p.</hi> 546. The perſon I plead exemption for from any harſh uſage muſt be of a converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on blameleſs, of an unſhaken beleif in all the eſſentials of Chriſtian Religion, of impregnable Loyalty, &amp;c. compliant with his Church to the utmoſt his Conſcience will permit. <hi>Item p.</hi> 543. That alſo is remarkable which <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewel <hi>in Defence of his Apol.</hi> Notes out of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in 19. <hi>Hom.</hi> on <hi>Matth. Nunquid ovis Lupum
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151109:40"/> per ſequitur aliquando, non ſed lupus ovem. Sic enim</hi> Cain <hi>perſecutus eſt</hi> Abel; <hi>non</hi> Abel Cain. <hi>Sic</hi> Iſhmael <hi>perſeoutus eſt</hi> Iſaac, <hi>ſic</hi> Judael <hi>Chriſtum, non Chriſtus</hi> Judaeos: <hi>Haeretici Chriſtianos, non Chriſtiani Haereticos. Ergo ex fructibus eorum cognoſcetis eos.</hi> And ſmartly again in the ſame <hi>Hom. Quem videris in ſanguine perſecutionis gauden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, lupus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Aſaph's <hi>Sermon on November</hi> 5th. 1680. <hi>p.</hi> 9. They give a ſtrong preſumption againſt themſelves that they are not truly Chriſtians. <hi>Item p.</hi> 20. Neither our Religion, nor our Church is of a perſecuting Spirit: I know not how it may be in particular perſons, but I ſay again, it is not the genius of our Church; ſhe hath no Doctrine that Teacheth Perſecution. She hath not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed it, as others when they were in the Authority. I thank God for it, and I hope ſhe will alwayes continue in that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Tillotſons <hi>Sermon on Novemb.</hi> 5th. 1678. <hi>Before the Houſe of Commons.</hi> Where he ſaith upon our Saviours words, ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of; not that ſurely which my doctrine deſigns to mould and faſhion you into, which is not a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and perſecuting and deſtructive Spirit, but mild and gentle and ſaving, tender of the lives and intereſts of men, even of thoſe who are our greateſt enemies. <hi>p.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>Item p.</hi> 30. True Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity is not only the beſt, but beſt natured inſtitution in the World, and ſo far as any Church is departed from good nature, and become cruel and barbarous, ſo far it is degenerated from Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hales <hi>of Erring Chriſtians;</hi> Wherefore if a perfect pattern of dealing with erring Chriſtians were to be ſought, there were not any like this of ours; which as it takes not to it ſelf the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of cruelty, ſo it leaves not any the liberty of deſtroying their own Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Caves <hi>Goſpel Preached to the Romans, Serm.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 89. 1680. Yea, ſuch of late hath been the tenderneſs and indulgence of our Gratious King and our Biſhops, that Mercy hath triumphed over Juſtice, and our Diſſenters have had more favour ſhewed them then the Laws allow: yet too many of them are as querulous and diſcontented ſtill, as ever, like froward humorous Children that cry, not becauſe of whipping, but becauſe they may not ſcratch their nurſes, and have their fooliſh wills in every thing.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151109:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Burnet <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury <hi>in his Remarks on the Methods for Converting of Prot. p.</hi> 30. Cites <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> ſaying, Let them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe cruelty upon you, who do not know with what difficulty truth is found out, and how hardly errours are avoided; and let them exerciſe cruelty upon you, who were never themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with any errour like that with which you (<hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees</hi>) are now deceived.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, Exhortation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, p.</hi> 15, 16. Violence alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates thoſe farther whom we ought to gain upon, and likewiſe increaſeth their party by the compaſſions of all good natured peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who are thereby firſt inclined to pity them, then to love them, and ſo the ſharpneſs of rigour inſtead of being a ſecurity often proves the ruine of thoſe who depend on it. <hi>Item, p.</hi> 29. I am ſure, we ought to carry it ſo towards them (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Papiſt) that it may appear we do not hate their perſons, and do nothing againſt them, but as we are compelled to it for ſelf-preſervation, and even in the hardeſt things that a prudent care of our own quiet and ſafety may force us to all perſonal ſoftneſs and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards them, is indiſpenſably neceſſary to ſuch as would ſhew themſelves to be truly reformed Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Haſcard <hi>on Eph.</hi> 4.32. <hi>And be ye kind one to another,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 24. 'Tis not the nature of God willingly to grieve the children of men, and ſhall we pleaſe our ſelves with ſeverities? — And muſt our dealings and converſations in rigours, in extremities, with our fellow Chriſtians, of the ſame ſtamp of nature and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with us, and ſo uſeful to us, be ſo far unlike to the methods of this mighty being?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True ſtate of Primitive Church, p.</hi> 8. As for thoſe who keep their erroneous opinions to themſelves, and onely refuſe to conform to the Churches eſtabliſhed Doctrine or Diſcipline, pardon me if I ſay that really I cannot find any warrant, or ſo much as any hint from the Goſpel to uſe any force to compel them; and from Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſure there is no motive to uſe force, becauſe (ſays he) as I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before, fear cannot make a man believe your doctrine, but only as an hypocrite profeſſes what he believes not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry,</hi> &amp;c. It becomes a Chriſtian Magiſtrate who conſiders he governs Men and not Beaſts, to afford means of Inſtruction and competent time for thoſe inſtructions to take place: It hath always been found, that Force without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction hath been prevalent onely on the worſt of men. —When
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151109:41"/> the Publick is ſecured, yet there is great ſcope for his Compaſſion; and conſequently it is the Duty of a good Magiſtrate to drive, as the Cattel can go, <hi>pag.</hi> 211, 212. Not to reſort to ſuch ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as are abhorred by all <hi>Engliſh-men, pag.</hi> 113.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Dodwel<hi>'s two Letters to Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>pag.</hi> 216. You mean that all truly Pious and Conſcientious perſons ought to be treated with Candor and Reſpect before ſevere means be uſed, or that the uſe of ſevere means is utterly to be forborn, as far as may be, that is, as far as ſuch forbearance may be reconcileable with the publick Intereſt, which is to be preferred before the private of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever; I could for my part heartily wiſh it were ſo too.</p>
            <p>Kidder<hi>'s Serm.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>pag.</hi> 22. We Quarrel firſt, then we hate and when we are ſtrong enough, we perſecute each other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Catholick Church, pag.</hi> 50. Men may make a noiſe with the <hi>Odious</hi> Names of Perſecutions, yet our Adverſaries of both the Extreams have little reaſon to object that, of which they themſelves ſtand ſo deeply chargeable, when in their power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Principles and Practices of Moderation,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe perſons (the Moderate Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) are deſirous that Mercy and Indulgence ſhould be ſhown towards thoſe, whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences will not permit them to comply with their Governours in ſome things diſputable, judging it a piece too near of kin to that of the cruel <hi>Procruſtres,</hi> ever to endeavour to force others to be juſt of their pitch and ſize in Opinions, and to approve of their Sentiments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Smythies <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs, pag.</hi> 68. As the <hi>Galathians</hi> were <hi>overtaken in a fault, Galat.</hi> 6.1. So we muſt account them likewiſe who have diſſented from us. Men that are guilty of Errours of practice, they are wilful, for they know they are wrong, and yet they are to be treated with a <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs,</hi> that they may be made ſenſible of their wickedneſs, that they may be reclaimed without puniſhment by the Execution of Laws, if it may be effected; Much more then are others to be dealt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly with in their Errors of Judgment through weakneſs and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Mind, for which they are to be pitied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformiſts Plea for the Nonconformiſts, Part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 28. Whether men ſhall forfeit their Goods and Liberties, for a Diſſent in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by any Goſpel-Rule, or Rules of Chriſtian Equity is a great Queſtion, and the Negative paſt doubt as yet.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151109:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem, Part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 5. The men ſpeaking of Diſſenters are given to pray, hear Sermons, ſing Pſalms, and other pious Exerciſes, and live, if not better, yet no worſe than many that go to Church: People think and ſay ſurely, it is hard to drive honeſt Mens Cattle, ſeize their goods, break open houſes, for doing well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument for Toleration and Indulgence in Difference of Opinion, Printed</hi> 1681, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. Inſtead of bearing and Indulging to compel a perſon to ſerve the Deity in a way againſt the light and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions he hath, is the greateſt Tyranny that can be; for it is to compel him to the doing of a thing, which on pain of Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he holds himſelf obliged not to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, pag.</hi> 5, 6. To be rigid and ſevere to others in matters of Opinion, is not to comport with the Golden Rule of all our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, preſcribed by our Bleſſed Saviour, which is <hi>to do as we would be done unto.</hi> Wouldſt thou be compelled thy ſelf to anothers opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that doſt compel others. —Arguments and Reaſons (and not Capiaſſes and Impriſonments, Fire and Faggot) are proper means to effect it: Thus the Ancient Fathers in all their Apologies to the Heaten in defence of themſelves and the Chriſtian Religion ever pleaded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Kettlewel<hi>'s Meaſure of Obedience, Edit.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 631. If we are rigorous and ſevere with our Brethren, God will be ſo with us alſo, and when he comes to judge us, we ſhall find as little allowance at his hands, as they have done at ours. For he ſhall have judgment from God without Mercy, who to men hath ſhewed no mercy: but if any man hath been merciful to his Brethren, God will be much more ſo to him. This will be the beſt Plea, that can be urged to obtain Mercy at Gods Hand, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:151109:42"/>
            <head>Peaceable Sentiments about Confeſſions and Articles of Faith.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIſhop</hi> Davenant<hi>'s Letter to</hi> Duraeus: Unleſs the Forms of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Confeſſions be reſtrained to neceſſary and uncontrovert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctrines, this miſchief will enſue; that many Learned, Pious, and peaceable Paſtors, will be excluded, and made unſerviceable to the Churches where they live; that therefore it doth behove the Rulers of the Church, as being conſcious of their own and of the infirmities of Mankind, to be cautious leaſt while they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a too rigid, and exact Confeſſion, they ſeem to weaken that ſweetly neceſſary Communion which ſhould be among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Seconds Declaration from</hi> Breda: That none for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit his Benefice that ſubſcribes all the Articles of Religion, which only concern the Confeſſion of the true Chriſtian Faith, and the Doctrine of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hiſtoria quinque Articularis, Part</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 8. <hi>Cited by Dr.</hi> Puller<hi>'s Moder. pag.</hi> 127. The Articles of this Proteſtant Church in the Infancy thereof were drawn up in general Terms, foreſeeing that Poſterity would grow up to fill the ſame; meaning, that thoſe Holy Men did prudently diſcover, that difference in Judgments would unavoidably happen in the Church, and were loth to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church any and drive them off from any Eccleſiaſtical Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for petty differences, which made them Pen the Articles in comprehenſive words to take in all who differing in Branches meet in the Root of the ſame Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Out of a Letter of the Biſhops of</hi> Rocheſter, Oxford, <hi>and St.</hi> Davids, <hi>to the Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 2. 1625. <hi>Exemplified in</hi> Heylin<hi>'s Hiſtory of Archbiſhop</hi> Laud, <hi>pag.</hi> 131. The Church of <hi>England</hi> when it was reformed from the Superſtitious Opinions broached
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151109:43"/> and maintained by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> refuſed their apparent and Dangerous Errors, and would not be too buſie with every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar School point. The Cauſe why ſhe held this Moderation was, becauſe ſhe could not be able to preſerve any Unity amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, if men were forced to ſubſcribe to curious particulars diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted in Schools. — Some of them [<hi>Montagues</hi> Opinions] are ſuch as are fit onely for Schools, and to be left at more Liberty for Learn'd Men to abound in their own Sence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor<hi>'s Ductor Dubitant, L.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>R,</hi> 28. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. No particular Church ought with rigour to require ſubſcription to Articles which are not evidently true and neceſſary to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, becauſe in the Diviſion of Hearts that is in the World, it is certain that ſome good men may diſſent; and then either they ſhall be afflicted, or tempted to Hypocriſie, either of which if Eccleſiaſtical Laws be guilty, they are not for Edification, they are neither Juſt, nor Pious, and therefore oblige not—.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Stillingfleet<hi>'s <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation, pag.</hi> 9. In the Preface. If any Temper can be found out, as to the manner of Subſcription, that may give eaſe to the ſcruples of our brethren, and ſecure the peace of the Church; and this I ſuppoſe may be done by an abſolute ſubſcription to all thoſe Articles which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Doctrine of the true Chriſtian Faith, and the uſe of the Sacraments, [even ſo Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi> required of the Clergy in <hi>Ireland</hi>] and a ſolemn Promiſe under their hands or Subſcription of peaceable ſubmiſſion as to the reſt, ſo as not to oppoſe or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict them, either in Preaching, or Writing, upon the ſame penalty as if they had not ſubſcribed to the 36.</p>
            <p>I ſhall mention two or three of thoſe Teſtimonies referred to in the Preface about Ordination. Dr. Chillingſworths <hi>Religion of Proteſtants, &amp;c. Epiſt.</hi> 1 <hi>ch.</hi> 6. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. by way of Queſtion; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any one kind of the external Forms of Church Government (<hi>i. e.</hi> by Biſhops or Presbyters) be ſo neceſſary to the being of a Church, but that they may be divers in divers places, and that a good and peaceable Chriſtian may and ought to ſubmit himſelf to the Government of the place where he lives, whoſoever he be. Which Queſtion (we are told in <hi>Iren.</hi> part. 2. ch. 8. p. 394.) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenour of the reſt to which it is joyned, muſt as to the former part be reſolved in the Negative, [no one Form of Church Government ſo neceſſary but they may be divers in divers places;] and as to the latter in the Affirmative [<hi>i. e.</hi> That a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151109:43"/> peaceable Chriſtian ought to ſubmit himſelf to the Government which he lives under.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge</hi> Hale's <hi>diſcourſe of Religion p.</hi> 11. That the Epiſcopal form of Government conſtituted in <hi>England</hi> is a moſt excellent Form of Eccleſiaſtical Government, and exceeds all others may eaſily be evinced; and that it is the beſt adapted to the Civil Government in this Kingdom is viſible to any intelligent perſon. And yet I do not think that the Eſſence of Chriſtian Religion conſiſts in this or any other particular Form of Government. —Though the wiſe and ſober ſort of Conformiſts know and profeſs this that a man may be a good and excellent Chriſtian under this Epiſcopal or any other Form of Church Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Carletons <hi>Conſenſus Eccleſ. Cathol. contra Trident, praelectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, c.</hi> 11. <hi>de Eccleſia p.</hi> 289. cited out of <hi>Conf. Plea for the Non-Conformiſt, part.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 36. It is the cuſtom of the Catholick Church, <hi>ut Epiſcopi legitime ordinent, ſed ſi quis a Presbytero Ordinatus fuerit, ordinatio illa etiam vera eſt ex ejuſdem Eccleſiae Catholicae judicio. Idem. p.</hi> 283. Ordination is not to be repeated, although it be diſorderly and out of courſe, any more than Baptiſm in the Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>But further even they who have the internal call, conſiſting of good Learning, Knowledge in the Scripture, and are of a good exemplary Converſation, and moved by the Spirit, are not to be reckoned as Laymen, but next to Presbyters or Miniſters, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the declared judgment of great and eminent Proteſtants, as <hi>Conf. Plea for Non Conformiſt, part.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 37. Arch-Biſhop <hi>Abbot</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this obſervation to the 9 Section of the 2d. ch. <hi>de Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; Baptiſmo. Quaeſtiones ſex diſcuſsae per</hi> Georgium <hi>Abbatium. p.</hi> 109.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> ſaith in <hi>Epiſt. ad Eph. c.</hi> 4. That ſome of the Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were admitted to read and interpret the Holy Scriptures, in the Primitive and purer Church; which they ſometimes did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in the preſence of the Biſhops; and nameth <hi>Origen</hi> and others. And ſaith he if any man add what the truly learned <hi>Hieron Zanchius</hi> ſpeaks indefinitely, — When from the practice of the purer Church, they who were not in Holy Orders, did Preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. We anſwer there is a difference to be made between the ſimple Layman, or the common ſort to whom power is given in the Roman Church to Baptize, and them who are <hi>inſtar Miniſtrorum Evangelii;</hi> and who not only excel the common ſort of men, for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151109:44"/> their Learning in holy things, but are (or were) called by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, publick and common Decree of the Biſhop and them ſet over the Congregation, publickly to interpret Scripture, And theſe, and not others the words of <hi>Bucer</hi> do note or point at, <hi>&amp;c. Iſtos ego non audeo ad ordinariorum, et vulgarium Laicorum conditiones revocare cum ad Presbyteros tam prope aceedant.</hi> I dare not bring down theſe to the condition of ordinary and vulgar Laymen, that come ſo near to Presbyters (or Miniſters) ſaith the Learned Abbot of this ſort. And whether <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeak of ſuch as theſe, that were permitted to Baptize, I leave to the Judgment of the Learned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewels <hi>Serm. on</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 223. In theſe our days the Miniſters of God, and Preachers of his Goſpel are evil ſpoken of among all men; ſome ſay they are unlearned, they are Crafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Some ſay they preach they cannot tell what. Let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and try their Doctrine with the touchſtone of Gods Word, and then be you Judges, if you ſee that we teach you nothing but the myſteries of God; that we diſcloſe to you the will of God, eſteem us to be the Servants of God, the Miniſters of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is but a taſte of what is referred to in <hi>Iren. part.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 8. and in <hi>Ccnf. Plea for Non-Conf. part.</hi> 3.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Hearty deſires and Prayers for Love and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIſhop</hi> Davenant<hi>'s Letter to</hi> Duraeus. That which all pious perſons are with fervent ſupplications to deſire they ought as earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to endeavour after. Now who doth not dayly ſolicit God for the peaceable State of the Church, who doth not pray that all thoſe things which vex, diſturb or any way hinder the Edification of the Church, ſhould be removed: this was the wiſh of the Royal Pſalmiſt, and ought to be the deſire of Princes, Doctors and all Chriſtians; and ſurely what they ſincerely ſhould deſire they ſhould as ſincerely endeavour after.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:151109:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall<hi>'s Works, pag.</hi> 426. Yea, let me beg peace as for Life, by your filial piety to the Church of God, by your love of Gods Truth, by the Graces of that one bleſſed Spirit, whereby we are all informed and quickned, by the precious Blood of the Son of God, ſhed for our Redemption be enclined to peace and Love, and though our brains be different let our hearts be one.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Treaty at</hi> Uxbridge, <hi>Ejac.</hi> 1. Oh thou that art the God of reaſon and of peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Soften our hearts by the bloud of our Redeemer, and perſwade us to accept of peace with thy ſelf, and both procure and preſerve peace among our ſelves as Men and Chriſtians. Condemn us not to our paſſions. Clear up our underſtandings to ſee thy Truth, and encline all our hearts to hold the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. Give us that Charity which ſhould be among our ſelves, and beſtow upon us that peace which onely Chriſt our great peace-maker can merit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Salisburies <hi>Exhortation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, p.</hi> 34. Let us all reſolve to ſpend ſome portion of our time, at leaſt an hour every Week in earneſt prayers to him for the peace of his <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> among us, and for continuing our Religion ſtill with us. It is his cauſe and we ought chiefly to offer it up to him for his protection and defence; and if our ſins do not defeat our prayers, we may hope that a conſiderable number of ſuch Interceſſions will procure great bleſſings to us; eſpecially we having the aſſiſtance of thoſe who have taken Sanctuary among us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Pygots Abners <hi>Plea for Accommodation, p.</hi> 15. Never leave wreſtling with the God of peace, by unceſſant and earneſt prayers, till he be entreated for the land to ſettle peace amongſt us, that the Lyon and the Lamb might lye down together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cauſes of decay of Chriſtian Piety, p.</hi> 419. Oh that we might ſee our impertinent ſtrifes ſuperſeded, and all moulded into the one Noble emulation, who ſhall faſteſt unravel his own miſchief, and promote that peace he hath hitherto diſturbed. This indeed were worthy to be the united deſign of all Learned men, and were it once ſo who knows how proſperous it might be, <hi>Item p.</hi> 227. Who knows what a powerful exorciſm the United Interceſſions of the Chriſtian World might have been, had we jointly deprecated our quarrels, God might have found a way to have compoſed them tho we could not.</p>
            <p>Forms of Prayer upon the Faſt Day 22d. <hi>Dec.</hi> 1680. In the prayer for Union amongſt our Selves; <hi>Bleſſed Jeſu, aur Saviour
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151109:45"/> and our Peace, — Look down in much Pity and Compaſſion upon this diſtreſſed Church and Nation, whoſe bleeding wounds occaſioned by the lamentable diviſions that are among us, cry aloud for thy ſpeedy help and ſaving relief, ſtir up we beſeech thee every Soul of us carefully (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſincere Chriſtians) to root out of our-hearts all Pride and vain Glory, all wrath and bitterneſs, all unjuſt prejudice and cauſeleſs jealouſie, all Hatred and Malice, and deſire of Revenge, and whatſoever it is that may any way exaſperate our minds, or hinder us from diſcerning the things that belong unto our peace.— That as there is but one body, and one Spirit, and one Hope of our Calling, one Lord, one Faith, &amp;c. So we may henceforth be all of one heart, and of one Soul, cloſely united in one Holy bond of Truth and Peace, of Faith and Charity; and (ſo far as it is poſſible and an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion is attainable) with one mind and one mouth glorifie God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Licenſed according to Order.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>A Table of the ſeveral Heads.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ACknowledged by Conformiſts that there are Good and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Men amongſt the Diſſenters.</item>
               <item>Salvation for ſuch as are faithful in the common duties of Chriſtianity.</item>
               <item>That Proteſtants are agreed in the main.</item>
               <item>The Creed contains all Truths neceſſary to Salvation.</item>
               <item>Conformiſts not forward in cenſuring men as guilty of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and damnable Errors.</item>
               <item>None to be ſhut out of the Church and denied Communion for leſſer ſins or Errors.</item>
               <item>That our Love muſt be Catholick.</item>
               <item>An Agreement of all Chriſtians in one Perſwaſion not to be expected.</item>
               <item>Mutual Favour and Forbearance to be practiſed in our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Judgments.</item>
               <item>Force and capital Severities, cenſured in matters of Religion.</item>
               <item>Of Confeſſions of Faith, and their Articles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
